<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-22T12:26:49-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ryleelyman.github.io</title><subtitle>Website / Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Choo Choo</title><link href="/2019/09/06/Choo-Choo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choo Choo" /><published>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2019/09/06/Choo-Choo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/09/06/Choo-Choo.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I posted my first paper, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.03097&quot;&gt;Train Tracks, Orbigraphs and CAT(0) Free-by-cyclic Groups&lt;/a&gt;
to the ArXiv! In it I give an extension to automorphisms of free products
of the algorithmic construction of relative train track maps for outer automorphisms
of free groups. I use it to prove that mapping tori of polynomially-growing automorphisms
of certain kinds are CAT(0) groups. I want to talk about the main ideas in the proof.
I haven’t addressed the question of “why” study these groups in this post, but
I will another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The length of the paper comes from constructing &lt;em&gt;relative train track maps&lt;/em&gt;
for outer automorphisms of free products. Relative train track maps
always seem to scare people who hear about them, so let me attempt an explanation of what’s going on.
The name and most motivations in the literature derive from the Nielsen–Thurston
normal forms for homotopy classes of surface homeomorphisms. My application
has a different feel, so let me attempt to sketch another connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to study a linear transformation
is by considering its eigenvalues, and thus
the dynamics of the linear transformations action on the associated vector space.
The Jordan normal form is designed to present
the dynamical properties of a linear transformation in a clean, easily understood way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given an automorphism of a free group &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F_n&lt;/script&gt;, its action on the homology of the free group
gives one a matrix in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\operatorname{GL}_n(\mathbb{Z})&lt;/script&gt;. However, since free groups
are nonabelian, this matrix tends to lose a lot of information about the automorphism
except in particular cases. A little better is the &lt;em&gt;transition matrix&lt;/em&gt; of a
self-map &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f\colon G \to G&lt;/script&gt; of a graph &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;G&lt;/script&gt; with fundamental group &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F_n&lt;/script&gt;. 
The &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;ij&lt;/script&gt;th entry of this matrix records how many times the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;-image of the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j&lt;/script&gt;th
edge crosses the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt;th edge in either direction. Here some information is lost again in general.
The point of a &lt;em&gt;relative train track map&lt;/em&gt; is to find such a map &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f\colon G \to G&lt;/script&gt; whose
transition matrix retains as much information as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Jordan normal form, the transition matrix for a relative train track map is
&lt;em&gt;block upper-triangular,&lt;/em&gt; corresponding to an increasing sequence of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;-invariant subgraphs.
Each square submatrix corresponding to a block is &lt;em&gt;irreducible.&lt;/em&gt; Polynomially-growing automorphisms
have (after taking powers) genuinely upper-triangular transition matrices with 1s on the diagonal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F_n = \langle x_1,\dotsc,x_n\rangle&lt;/script&gt;, let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi&lt;/script&gt; be an automorphism and suppose
that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Phi(x_i) = u_ix_iv_i&lt;/script&gt;, where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i,v_i \in \langle x_1,\dotsc,x_{i-1}\rangle&lt;/script&gt;.
In the free-by-cyclic group &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F_n\rtimes_\Phi\mathbb{Z} = \langle x_1,\dotsc,x_n,t\rangle&lt;/script&gt;,
this gives us the relation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;tx_it^{-1} = u_ix_iv_i&lt;/script&gt;, which we can rewrite as
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_i^{-1}u_i^{-1}tx_i = v_it&lt;/script&gt;, which, if you squint, starts to look like a relation in
an HNN extension with stable letter &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_i&lt;/script&gt;. In fact, by our assumption on &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_i&lt;/script&gt;,
we actually do get a description of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F_n\rtimes\mathbb{Z}&lt;/script&gt; as an iterated HNN extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation can be good and bad. Gersten gave an example of such a description of a free-by-cyclic
group which is a “poison subgroup” for nonpositive curvature. There, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_i&lt;/script&gt;
are such that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i^{-1}t&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_it&lt;/script&gt; have no business being conjugate in a nice action on a CAT(0) space.
On the other hand, in the situation where they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be conjugate,
Bridson–Haefliger give a construction that allows you to bootstrap a
geometric action on a CAT(0) space up the HNN extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I realized, was that in the class of automorphisms I was studying,
if it were the case that the automorphism was already upper-triangular
with respect to the basis &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x_1,\dotsc,x_n&lt;/script&gt; we were handed, then
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i^{-1}t&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_it&lt;/script&gt; were &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; conjugate, so Bridson–Haefliger says we win.
So, my goal in constructing relative train track maps was to find a basis
that has this nice property for a (power of) an arbitrary polynomially-growing
outer automorphism. In the paper, the application is in Section 7, while the
heavy lifting is to find a way to adapt the relative train track technology appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since relative train track maps with nice properties have become a foundational
tool in the study of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\operatorname{Out}(F_n)&lt;/script&gt;, my hope is that this construction
will help in the study of outer automorphism groups of free products.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I posted my first paper, Train Tracks, Orbigraphs and CAT(0) Free-by-cyclic Groups to the ArXiv! In it I give an extension to automorphisms of free products of the algorithmic construction of relative train track maps for outer automorphisms of free groups. I use it to prove that mapping tori of polynomially-growing automorphisms of certain kinds are CAT(0) groups. I want to talk about the main ideas in the proof. I haven’t addressed the question of “why” study these groups in this post, but I will another time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Lay Of The Land</title><link href="/2019/07/13/The-Lay-of-the-Land.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lay Of The Land" /><published>2019-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2019/07/13/The-Lay-of-the-Land</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/07/13/The-Lay-of-the-Land.html">&lt;p&gt;In a poor attempt to remain interesting to the non-mathematically inclined
reader, maybe it would be good to begin with a few words about the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern mathematics, there are two notions that might be truly called 
foundational to all the work we do. These are &lt;em&gt;set theory&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;category theory.&lt;/em&gt;
Both theories are living, evolving things with their specialists, constructions
and interesting problems, just like any other field of math, 
but the core ideas are familiar and useful to nearly every mathematician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;set,&lt;/em&gt; naively, is just a way to collect a bunch of objects (called &lt;em&gt;elements&lt;/em&gt;)
together. Since a set only cares about membership or lack thereof, duplicate
elements are ignored. When we’re explicit about them, a set is typically
denoted as a list of elements (thought of as unordered), surrounded by curly braces.
So as sets, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\{1,2,3,3,5\} = \{1,2,3\}&lt;/script&gt;. A set comprises its elements, nothing more,
nothing less. Thus, maps or functions &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt; between sets &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/script&gt; are just
assignments: to each element &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x&lt;/script&gt; in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X$, we assign a (unique) element&lt;/script&gt;f(x)&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;of&lt;/script&gt;Y$$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things, mathematical objects, whatever you can pin down in language,
may be elements (or not) of sets. Sets may even be elements of other sets, although
here is a source of worry. Bertrand Russell observed in 1901 that allowing this
kind of willy-nilly calling things sets yields the mathematical equivalent of the
following silly story: In a small village there is one barber. He shaves the
beards of only those men who does not shave themselves. Who shaves the barber?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question, of course, has no good answer. If the barber shaves himself, then
he cannot, but then he must. The mathematical response to Russell’s realization
was to retrench a bit, but it also paved the way for set theory to become an 
interesting field of research in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set theory, thanks to work of Kurt Goedel and many others, has raised thorny,
even unsolvable, problems that mathematicians working in other fields would often
prefer to gloss over. One example is the following: If you have in front of you
a finite collection of sets, maybe think of them as baskets in the produce section,
you can obviously choose an element from each basket. This process is sometimes
called a &lt;em&gt;choice function.&lt;/em&gt; If you imagine an infinitely long aisle at the grocery
store with baskets evenly spaced along it, you might agree that you can still
choose one element from each basket. Even though you won’t live to see it
through, it’s easy to describe a way to decide how to choose the next element;
each basket is eventually reached by you, even though you will never reach 
every basket. This kind of infinity is &lt;em&gt;countably infinite,&lt;/em&gt; like the numbers
we use for counting. But there are more kinds of infinity, and in those cases
it’s maybe not immediately clear that we should still be able to take an object from
each basket. The hypothesis that we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; is called the &lt;em&gt;Axiom of Choice,&lt;/em&gt; and it
turns out to be “independent” of the rest of the rules of set theory we commonly employ.
That is, the rest of set theory &lt;em&gt;can remain true&lt;/em&gt; whatever position we wish to take on
the axiom of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category theory, (already touched on implicitly in &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs.html&quot;&gt;The Category of Graphs&lt;/a&gt;) has
a somewhat similar history, although it arose later. Introduced by Samuel Eilenberg
and Saunders Mac Lane in their study of algebraic topology, it has since become
a central perspective in many areas of mathematics and also grown into a field
of interest in its own right. A category is a collection of objects and arrows.
Note that I did not say a &lt;em&gt;set.&lt;/em&gt; This distinction is important theoretically
but in practice categorical and set-theoretic reasoning are typically 
sufficiently different that this can be ignored. In category theory,
the sets themselves comprise a category, typically called &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; with
objects sets and arrows functions between sets. This metaphor motivates
the definition: arrows have a &lt;em&gt;domain&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;codomain,&lt;/em&gt; just as functions
between sets do. Arrows, like functions, may be &lt;em&gt;composed&lt;/em&gt; (i.e.
“first add four, and then multiply by sixteen”), and the composition is
associative, but need not be commutative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This general picture allows one to talk about several different, yet related,
situations together at once. Many common constructions in mathematics, including
“sum” and “product” may be phrased as a certain kind of “universal” construction
in the language of category theory. One such construction, the &lt;em&gt;free object,&lt;/em&gt;
is particularly interesting within group theory. Originally I had meant to talk
about it in this post, but perhaps the next one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In a poor attempt to remain interesting to the non-mathematically inclined reader, maybe it would be good to begin with a few words about the landscape.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Category Of Graphs</title><link href="/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Category Of Graphs" /><published>2019-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs.html">&lt;p&gt;You know the sensation where a familiar word becomes suddenly
completely &lt;em&gt;strange&lt;/em&gt; for no apparent reason? Like suddenly the scales
fall away from your eyes and you see how utterly weird it is that a
concept has a particular name? I’ve been having that feeling with the
word &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt; as I use it in math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a kid, you learn how to &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt; simple functions in the sense of 
being able to sketch them on a sheet of, say, &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt; paper. Millions
of adults probably faintly remember the shape of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y = x^2&lt;/script&gt; but aren’t
quite sure why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mathematicians and computer scientists, though, for some reason &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt;
means something similar, but different: to them a graph is an object with
&lt;em&gt;vertices&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt;. Indeed, to Serre, that’s literally all a graph is:
a quadruple &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(V,E,\bar{},\iota)&lt;/script&gt;. Two sets, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E&lt;/script&gt;, represent the
vertices and (oriented) edges of the graph, and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\bar{}\colon E \to E&lt;/script&gt; and
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\iota\colon E \to V&lt;/script&gt; are functions; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\bar{e}&lt;/script&gt; is the edge &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt; with its
orientation reversed, (so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\bar{\bar{e}} = e&lt;/script&gt; for any edge &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt;, but
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\bar e \neq e&lt;/script&gt;), and
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\iota(e)&lt;/script&gt; represents the initial vertex of the edge &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt;. This lets us
define a function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau\colon E \to V&lt;/script&gt; picking out the &lt;em&gt;terminal&lt;/em&gt; vertex
of an edge by setting &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau(e) = \iota(\bar{e})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topologist would prefer to say that a graph is a 1-dimensional CW complex.
So rather than an abstract set of vertices, we have a set of points, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt;,
the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0&lt;/script&gt;-cells of our CW complex. And rather than an abstract set of oriented
edges, we have a collection of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt;-cells (intervals of the real line) 
whose endpoints are attached to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0&lt;/script&gt;-cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two descriptions really are in agreement for most purposes. Maybe one would
prefer the more combinatorial description as a way of “rigidifying” some of the
inherent floppiness of topological spaces. At the same time, using topological methods
allows one access to a whole host of techniques that a too-rigid approach might bury
under a sea of formalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, neither definition really squares with the idea of the graph of
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y = x^2&lt;/script&gt;, hence why I’ve been feeling weird about the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the &lt;em&gt;category of graphs&lt;/em&gt;, introduced by John Stallings in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.math.ou.edu/~nbrady/teaching/s11-5863/stallings.pdf&quot;&gt;Topology of Finite Graphs&lt;/a&gt;,
building on work of Serre in &lt;a href=&quot;https://d-nb.info/965816907/04&quot;&gt;Trees&lt;/a&gt;, more about which
almost certainly soon, has (as all categories do)
collections of objects and arrows between them.
Here the objects are graphs and arrows are &lt;em&gt;morphisms of graphs.&lt;/em&gt; 
A morphism &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f\colon G \to H&lt;/script&gt; between
graphs &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;G&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H&lt;/script&gt; is a pair of functions &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f_V\colon V(G) \to V(H)&lt;/script&gt; 
and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f_E\colon E(G) \to E(H)&lt;/script&gt;, such that the following diagrams commute:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\require{AMScd}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\begin{CD}
E(G) @&gt;f_E&gt;&gt; E(H) \\
@V{\iota}VV @V{\iota}VV \\
V(G) @&gt;f_V&gt;&gt; V(H)
\end{CD}\qquad
\begin{CD}
E(G) @&gt;f_E&gt;&gt; E(H) \\
@V\bar{}VV @V\bar{}VV \\
E(G) @&gt;f_E&gt;&gt; E(H)
\end{CD}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In English what this is saying is that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt; preserves the graph structure:
it sends edges to edges, vertices to vertices, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\bar e&lt;/script&gt; are sent
to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f(e)&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{f(e)}&lt;/script&gt;, and the initial vertex of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt; is
sent to the initial vertex of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f(e)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stallings emphasizes the rigidity of morphisms in this construction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By graph and map of graphs, I mean something purely combinatorial or
algebraic. Pictures can be drawn, but one has to understand that maps are
rigid and not just continuous, maps do not collapse edges or wrap edges
around several edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s true; it’s a little challenging to describe precisely which
topological maps between graphs are even homotopic to morphisms without
giving the game (Stallings’ paper) away too quickly!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You know the sensation where a familiar word becomes suddenly completely strange for no apparent reason? Like suddenly the scales fall away from your eyes and you see how utterly weird it is that a concept has a particular name? I’ve been having that feeling with the word graph as I use it in math.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World</title><link href="/2019/06/22/Hello-World.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" /><published>2019-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2019/06/22/Hello-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/06/22/Hello-World.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week,
Marc Weidenbaum of &lt;a href=&quot;https://disquiet.com&quot;&gt;disquiet.com&lt;/a&gt; wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://disquiet.com/2019/06/16/word-blog-20th-anniversary-1999/&quot;&gt;paean
to the blog&lt;/a&gt; that I found really inspiring. “Self-publishing,”
he writes, “is the heart of the healthy internet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So hello. Having been given the push I needed, I decided to
move my academic website to its own URL and use it as an excuse 
to start blogging. Since much of the rest of this website is
given over to my career as a mathematician, it’s reasonable to
expect that I will talk about math here, and I expect to get
technical with it when I want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math is not my only passion. I expect to also talk about
many things related to music. This blog is tentatively titled
Alanza, my middle name, but also my “artist moniker” when 
playing solo. I am a moderator on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co&quot;&gt;lines forum&lt;/a&gt;,
also under the name Alanza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This site is built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and hosted on
GitHub Pages. On lines I asked several questions about how to get
up and running with a website and got &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co/t/blogging-platforms/23333?u=alanza&quot;&gt;a wealth of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;
in response. Although, being a millenial, it’s maybe not surprising
that I’d messed around with HTML as a kid, this site is my first time
using CSS. I read what I could on &lt;a href=&quot;https://every-layout.dev&quot;&gt;Every Layout&lt;/a&gt;
to get a feel for what the concerns were, and borrowed their “Sidebar”
primitive. I also appreciated the from-square-one approach of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://internetingishard.com&quot;&gt;Internetting Is Hard&lt;/a&gt; when Every Layout
went over my head. These resources helped get me up to “okay, I can
Google that” speed.
I also should shout out &lt;a href=&quot;https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2018/08/05/mathjax-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Arthur O’Dwyer&lt;/a&gt; for a helpful
blog post about enabling MathJax in Jekyll—which turns out to be 
surprisingly simple!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I taught myself a lot of the basics of typesetting,
so it was eye-opening to see how very different the concerns are
when designing for the web. Although the design here is certainly
minimal, it was also surprisingly relatively painless!
One of my goals for this year has been to improve my Vim skills
and incorporate it more into my work. I was very pleased how well
using Jekyll vs. say, WordPress, furthers this goal!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Earlier this week, Marc Weidenbaum of disquiet.com wrote a paean to the blog that I found really inspiring. “Self-publishing,” he writes, “is the heart of the healthy internet.”</summary></entry></feed>