<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-22T13:09:45-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ryleelyman.github.io</title><subtitle>Website / Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hello World</title><link href="/2019/06/22/Hello-World.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" /><published>2019-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2019/06/22/Hello-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/06/22/Hello-World.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week,
Marc Weidenbaum of &lt;a href=&quot;https://disquiet.com&quot;&gt;disquiet.com&lt;/a&gt; wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://disquiet.com/2019/06/16/word-blog-20th-anniversary-1999/&quot;&gt;paean
to the blog&lt;/a&gt; that I found really inspiring. “Self-publishing,”
he writes, “is the heart of the healthy internet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So hello. Having been given the push I needed, I decided to
move my academic website to its own URL and use it as an excuse 
to start blogging. Since much of the rest of this website is
given over to my career as a mathematician, it’s reasonable to
expect that I will talk about math here, and I expect to get
technical with it when I want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math is not my only passion. I expect to also talk about
many things related to music. This blog is tentatively titled
Alanza, my middle name, but also my “artist moniker” when 
playing solo. I am a moderator on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co&quot;&gt;lines forum&lt;/a&gt;,
also under the name Alanza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This site is built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and hosted on
GitHub Pages. On lines I asked several questions about how to get
up and running with a website and got &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co/t/blogging-platforms/23333?u=alanza&quot;&gt;a wealth of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;
in response. Although, being a millenial, it’s maybe not surprising
that I’d messed around with HTML as a kid, this site is my first time
using CSS. I read what I could on &lt;a href=&quot;https://every-layout.dev&quot;&gt;Every Layout&lt;/a&gt;
to get a feel for what the concerns were, and borrowed their “Sidebar”
primitive. I also appreciated the from-square-one approach of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://internetingishard.com&quot;&gt;Internetting Is Hard&lt;/a&gt; when Every Layout
went over my head. These resources helped get me up to “okay, I can
Google that” speed.
I also should shout out &lt;a href=&quot;https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2018/08/05/mathjax-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Arthur O’Dwyer&lt;/a&gt; for a helpful
blog post about enabling MathJax in Jekyll—which turns out to be 
surprisingly simple!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I taught myself a lot of the basics of typesetting,
so it was eye-opening to see how very different the concerns are
when designing for the web. Although the design here is certainly
minimal, it was also surprisingly relatively painless!
One of my goals for this year has been to improve my Vim skills
and incorporate it more into my work. I was very pleased how well
using Jekyll vs. say, WordPress, furthers this goal!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Earlier this week, Marc Weidenbaum of disquiet.com wrote a paean to the blog that I found really inspiring. “Self-publishing,” he writes, “is the heart of the healthy internet.”</summary></entry></feed>