<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-29T12:26:40-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ryleelyman.github.io</title><subtitle>Website / Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Train Track Algorithm For Graphs Of Groups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/The-Train-Track-Algorithm-for-Graphs-of-Groups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Train Track Algorithm For Graphs Of Groups" /><published>2020-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/The-Train-Track-Algorithm-for-Graphs-of-Groups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/The-Train-Track-Algorithm-for-Graphs-of-Groups.html">&lt;p&gt;Train track maps, which also come in “relative” and other flavors,
are particularly nice homotopy equivalences of graphs
used as tools to reason about outer automorphisms of free groups.
I wrote a paper extending train track maps (as well as relative train track maps and “CTs”)
to graphs of groups (with trivial edge groups for CTs).
In this post I want to talk a little about how to think about train track maps
and (“tame” in some sense) homotopy equivalences of graphs of groups more generally.
At the end of the post I talk through using the train track algorithm
to compute an example coming from a pseudo-Anosov 5-braid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background-on-graphs-of-groups&quot;&gt;Background on graphs of groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a little background for anyone reading who isn’t an expert in graphs of groups.
The standard reference is Chapter 1 of Serre’s book &lt;em&gt;Trees,&lt;/em&gt; 
which is terse but very good.
Group actions on trees (i.e. simply connected, 1-dimensional simplicial complexes)
crop up all over the place in the theory of infinite groups.
A &lt;em&gt;graph of groups&lt;/em&gt; is a kind of “orbifold quotient” of a group action on a tree.
Technically one needs to assume that the action satisfies the condition of
“no inversions in edges” which means what it probably sounds like
and can always be accomplished by passing to the barycentric subdivision of the tree.
Under this hypothesis, the quotient space of the action is naturally a graph
(i.e. a 1-dimensional CW complex, which will be connected).
Attached to the vertices and edges of the graph are groups
recording stabilizer information.
The “no inversions in edges” hypothesis ensures that if an edge is stabilized by a group element,
then so are the incident vertices,
so there are injective homomorphisms from edge groups into incident vertex groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to like thinking categorically,
a graph of groups can be succinctly described this way.
A graph \(\Gamma\) describes a small category \(\Gamma\) whose objects are the cells of \(\Gamma\)
and whose nonidentity arrows run from edges to incident vertices.
A graph of groups is a functor from the small category \(\Gamma\)
to the category of groups with arrows monomorphisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental theorem of Bass–Serre theory asserts a perfect correspondence between
groups acting on trees on the one hand and graphs of groups on the other.
The exciting part of the theorem says that given a graph of groups,
there is a group, called the &lt;em&gt;fundamental group of the graph of groups&lt;/em&gt;
and a tree, called the &lt;em&gt;Bass–Serre tree&lt;/em&gt; on which it acts
so that the quotient graph of groups is the given graph of groups.
By the way, the fundamental group is really a group of homotopy classes of loops
in the right sense.
In the language of orbifolds, every graph of groups is “good.”
What’s more, a simple presentation of the fundamental group of the graph of groups
can be written down, and the tree and action explicitly described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;morphisms-and-maps-of-graphs-of-groups&quot;&gt;Morphisms and maps of graphs of groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s call a continuous map of graphs a &lt;em&gt;morphism&lt;/em&gt; if it sends vertices to vertices and edges to edges.
There is a notion, due to Bass, of a &lt;em&gt;morphism&lt;/em&gt; of graphs of groups.
It’s a little complicated, so I’d rather talk around it than give a formal definition here.
Suppose \(G\) and \(G'\) are groups acting on trees \(T\) and \(T'\), respectively,
and suppose that we have a homomorphism \(f_\sharp\colon G \to G'\).
A morphism \(\tilde f\colon T \to T'\) is &lt;em&gt;equivariant&lt;/em&gt; with respect to \(f_\sharp\) 
if for all \(g \in G\) and \(x \in T\), we have&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tilde f(g.x) = f_\sharp(g).\tilde f(x).\]

&lt;p&gt;If \(\mathcal{G}\) and \(\mathcal{G}'\) are the quotient graphs of groups,
Bass’s definition is designed so that in this situation there is a morphism \(f\colon\mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\).
Conversely, given a morphism of graphs of groups \(f\colon \mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\),
there is a map \(f_\sharp\colon G \to G'\) and an equivariant map \(\tilde f\colon T\to T'\).
The correspondence is not quite perfect—in some situations there are multiple morphisms of graphs of groups
yielding the same pair \(f_\sharp\) and \(\tilde f\),
but the difference is understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one happens to be categorically minded, it’s possible to give a succinct definition 
of a morphism of graphs of groups.
Suppose \(\mathcal{G}\) and \(\mathcal{G}'\) are graphs of groups with underlying graphs
\(\Gamma\) and \(\Gamma'\), respectively.
A morphism of graphs \(f\colon \Gamma \to \Gamma'\) yields a functor of the associated small categories.
(Indeed, one could eke out slightly more generality 
by defining morphisms of graphs to be those maps yielding a functor of small categories.)
A morphism of graphs of groups is a morphism of underlying graphs \(f\colon \Gamma \to \Gamma'\)
and a &lt;em&gt;pseudonatural transformation&lt;/em&gt; of functors \(f\colon \mathscr{G} \Rightarrow \mathscr{G}'f\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now suppose we have an automorphism \(f_\sharp\colon G \to G\) and a map
\(\tilde f \colon T \to T\) which is equivariant with respect to \(f_\sharp\) 
but may not be a morphism.
After performing a homotopy, 
we may assume that \(\tilde f\) 
is a linear embedding on each edge, 
expanding it over an edge path.
Now \(\tilde f\) will become a morphism after (equivariantly) subdividing each edge into finitely many edges,
so on the quotient graph of groups we are interested in maps 
which may be represented as a subdivision followed by a morphism.
Such a map \(f\colon \mathcal{G}\to\mathcal{G}\) sends vertices to vertices and edges to paths in the graph of groups.
If additionally the image of each edge is a &lt;em&gt;tight&lt;/em&gt; path, i.e. it cannot be shortened by a homotopy,
we’ll call such a map a &lt;em&gt;topological representative.&lt;/em&gt;
For (many) examples of this kind of map, hang on for one more section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;train-track-maps&quot;&gt;Train track maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train track maps were introduced by Bestvina and Handel in their 1992 paper
“Train tracks and automorphisms of free groups”
to study outer automorphisms of free groups.
They remain one of the main tools for their study.
A topological representative is a &lt;em&gt;train track map&lt;/em&gt; if for each edge \(e\),
the path \(f^k(e))\) is immersed for all \(k \ge 1\),
i.e. it cannot be shortened by a homotopy.
If one accepts immersions and homotopy in a graph of groups sense,
the same definition works for both topological representatives on graphs and on graphs of groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bestvina and Handel describe an algorithm that takes as input an arbitrary topological representative
and progressively either improves it to a train track map or finds an invariant subgraph.
(It is &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; possible to be both a train track map and have an invariant subgraph, 
but these cases are of less interest.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument is a beautiful application of the Perron–Frobenius theory of nonnegative integer matrices.
A nonnegative integer matrix \(M\) is &lt;em&gt;irreducible&lt;/em&gt; if for each \(i\) and \(j\) there exists \(k\)
such that the \(ij\)th entry of \(M^k\) is positive.
To a topological representative \(f\colon \mathcal{G} \to \mathcal{G}\) we can associate a &lt;em&gt;transition matrix&lt;/em&gt;
with rows and columns for each edge of the underlying graph \(\Gamma\)
and \(ij\)th entry the number of times the image of the \(j\)th edge crosses the \(i\)th edge in either direction.
It turns out that the transition matrix of \(f\) is irreducible exactly when \(f\) has no invariant subgraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each irreducible matrix has a real &lt;em&gt;Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue&lt;/em&gt; \(\lambda\) satisfying \(\lambda \ge 1\).
If \(f\) is not a train track map, Bestvina and Handel argue, then the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue may be decreased
by their algorithm.
But by arguing that the number of edges of the graphs they consider remains bounded,
the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue can only be decreased finitely many times before reaching a minimum,
at which point a train track map is reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-pseudo-anosov-braid-example&quot;&gt;A pseudo-Anosov braid example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the algorithm and hopefully offer some illumination on how to think about maps of graphs of groups,
I’d like to compute a train track map for the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0506295&quot;&gt;pseudo-Anosov 5-braid with the least dilatation,&lt;/a&gt;
\(\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\),
seen as an (outer) automorphism of \(W_5\), the free product of 5 copies of the cyclic group of order 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write&lt;/p&gt;

\[W_5 = \langle a_1,a_2,\dotsc,a_5 \mid a_1^2 = a_2^2 = \dotsb = a_5^2 = 1 \rangle.\]

&lt;p&gt;There is a homomorphism from the braid group \(B_n\) to \(\operatorname{Aut}(W_n)\)
sending the generator \(\sigma_i\) to the automorphism&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{cases}
a_i \mapsto a_ia_{i+1}a_i^{-1} \\
a_{i+1} \mapsto a_i \\
a_j \mapsto a_j &amp;amp; j \neq i, i+1.
\end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;There’s a good reason (involving orbifolds) that the homomorphism sends
pseudo-Anosov braids to (outer) automorphisms representable by irreducible train track maps,
but let us just remark that we expect our eventual train track map to have
Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue equal to the dilatation of \(\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\),
that is, \(\lambda \approx 1.722\), the largest root of \(x^4 - x^3 - x^2 - x + 1\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the homomorphism, the action of our element on the generators of \(W_5\) is given by&lt;/p&gt;

\[\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\begin{cases}
a_1 \mapsto a_1a_2a_3a_2^{-1}a_1^{-1} \\
a_2 \mapsto a_1a_2a_4a_2^{-1}a_1^{-1} \\
a_3 \mapsto a_1a_2a_1^{-1} \\
a_4 \mapsto a_1a_5a_1^{-1} \\
a_5 \mapsto a_1.
\end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;To start, we need a graph of groups with fundamental group \(W_5\).
It is a fact that if all edge groups in a graph of groups are trivial,
and the underlying graph is a tree,
then the fundamental group of the graph of groups is isomorphic to the free product of the vertex groups.
Thus a good candidate is the following graph of groups \(\mathcal{G}_1\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/thistle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A graph of groups with fundamental group $$W_5$$&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one vertex with trivial vertex group, five vertices with vertex group cyclic of order 2,
represented in the image by a number 2,
and five edges, each one connecting a vertex with nontrivial vertex group to the vertex with trivial vertex group.
Let us base the fundamental group at the center vertex with trivial vertex group.
Under our identification of this fundamental group with \(W_5\),
a generator of \(W_5\) is represented by a loop that travels out along an edge,
picks up the nontrivial element of the vertex group, and then travels back.
Thus for example \(a_2\) is represented by the loop \(\bar Ba_2B\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s introduce some notation: 
I’ll write a period for the nontrivial element of any vertex group,
and write a hat above an edge to mean traveling along the edge, 
picking up the nontrivial element of the vertex group and then traveling back.
Thus the group element \(a_1a_2a_3a_2^{-1}a_1^{-1}\) is represented in our graph of groups
by the loop \(\hat A\hat B\hat C\hat B\hat A\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may represent \(\sigma_1\sigma_1\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\) by the map
\(f_1\colon \mathcal{G}_1\to\mathcal{G}_1\) defined as&lt;/p&gt;

\[f_1 \begin{cases}
A \mapsto C\hat B \hat A \\
B \mapsto D\hat B \hat A \\
C \mapsto B \hat A \\
D \mapsto E \hat A \\
E \mapsto A
\end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;The transition matrix of \(f_1\) is&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{pmatrix}
2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 1 \\
2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\
1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0
\end{pmatrix},\]

&lt;p&gt;whose Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_1\) is the largest real root of
\(-x^5 + 4x^4 + 2x^3 + 4x + 1\) and satisfies \(\lambda_1 \approx 4.577\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we decide whether \(f_1\) is a train track map?
Since \(f_1\) sends edges to tight edge paths,
the only place where cancellation could occur is where the images of edges are joined together.
For example, in \(f_1^2(A)\), there is cancellation between \(f_1(B)\) and \(f_1(\bar A)\)
because the last edge of \(f_1(B)\), namely \(A\), is equal to the reverse of the first edge of \(f_1(\bar A)\).
Thus we know \(f_1\) is not a train track map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can formalize this as follows: a &lt;em&gt;turn&lt;/em&gt; is a pair of edges sharing a common initial vertex,
e.g. \(\{\bar A,\bar A\}\) or \(\{\bar B,\bar C\}\).
The former turn is &lt;em&gt;degenerate,&lt;/em&gt; while the latter is not.
If the vertex in question has nontrivial vertex group,
rather than just pairs of edges,
we should consider pairs of pairs consisting of an edge together with a vertex group element.
Thus at the initial vertex of the edge \(A\),
the turn \(\{.A,A\}\) is nondegenerate.
A topological representative \(f\colon \mathcal{G} \to \mathcal{G}\) induces a map \(Tf\)
on the set of turns by sending \(\{E,E'\}\) to the
turn determined by the initial edges in the image of \(f(E)\) and \(f(E')\).
A turn is &lt;em&gt;illegal&lt;/em&gt; if it is eventually mapped to a degenerate turn.
In our example, every turn based at the center vertex is illegal because
each such turn is mapped to \(\{\bar A,\bar A\}\).
Thus we can say that \(f_1\) is not a train track map
because, for instance, the image of \(f_1(A)\) contains the illegal turn \(\{\bar B,\bar A\}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the situation, let’s &lt;em&gt;fold&lt;/em&gt; \(\bar A\) and \(\bar B\). 
They each have initial segments mapped to the path \(\hat A\hat B\),
so subdivide at the endpoint of these initial segments and then identify them to create a new edge as pictured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/fold1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Folding the edges $$\bar A$$ and $$\bar B$$&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The correspondence \(A \leadsto A'F\) and \(B \leadsto B'F\) allows us to define
a new map on our new graph of groups \(f_2\colon \mathcal{G}_2\to \mathcal{G}_2\).
The new map admits some tightening, which yields a corresponding reduction in the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue
\(\lambda_2\),
which is now the largest root of the polynomial \(x^6 - 2x^5 - 2x^4 - 4x^2 + 3x + 2\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_2 \approx 2.994\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The second topological representative&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the map \(f_2\) is still not a train track map, 
since every turn based at either of the vertices with trivial vertex stabilizer is eventually mapped to
\(\{\bar F,\bar F\}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The second map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s fold again, this time identifying all of \(E\) with an initial segment of \(\bar F\).
The correspondence \(F \leadsto F'E\) yields a new map \(f_3\colon \mathcal{G}_3 \to \mathcal{G}_3\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The third topological representative&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_3\) is the largest root of
\(x^6 - 2x^5 - 2x^4 - 2x^3 + 5x - 2\) and satisfies \(\lambda_3 \approx 2.875\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The third map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still illegal turns, so let’s fold \(C\) and \(D\) with \(E\) to produce a valence-one vertex
with trivial vertex group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/fold3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The third fold&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folding doesn’t produce any cancellation, so the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue is unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The fourth and fifth maps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The valence-one homotopy does decrease the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue;
\(\lambda_5\) is the largest root of \(-x^5 + x^4 + x^3 + x^2 + x - 2\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_5 \approx 1.830\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The fifth map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image of \(F'\) contains the illegal turn \(\{\bar A',\bar B'\}\),
which is first mapped to \(\{\bar C',\bar D'\}\) before degenerating.
So we’ll fold \(\bar D'\) and \(\bar C'\), then \(\bar A'\) and \(\bar B'\), 
and then the interior of \(F'\) if need be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The sixth and seventh maps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, the second fold produces nontrivial tightening;
\(\lambda_7\) is the largest root of \(-x^7 + x^6 + x^5 + x^4 + x^3 - 2x^2 - 2\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_7 \approx 1.789\).
We have produced a vertex of valence two with trivial vertex group and would like to get rid of it via a homotopy.
The eigenvector coefficient of the edge \(G\) is larger than the eigenvector coefficient for \(F'\),
so we collapse \(G\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The eighth map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_8\) is the largest root of
\(x^6 - x^5 - 2x^3 - x - 1\) and satisfies \(\lambda_8 \approx 1.783\).
The turn \(\{\bar E',\bar F'\}\) is illegal and in the image of \(F'\), so we fold them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The ninth map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_9\) is the largest root of \(x^6 - x^5 - 2x^3 - x + 1\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_9 \approx 1.722\).
The only turns that we need to worry about in the image of edges of \(f_9\) are \(\{E',\bar F''\}\)
and \(\{\bar B'',F''\}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The ninth map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, both of these turns are legal, so this is a train track map!
Indeed \(\lambda_9\) is also the largest real root of \(x^4 - x^3 - x^2 - x + 1\),
the polynomial we mentioned before in connection with \(\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Train track maps, which also come in “relative” and other flavors, are particularly nice homotopy equivalences of graphs used as tools to reason about outer automorphisms of free groups. I wrote a paper extending train track maps (as well as relative train track maps and “CTs”) to graphs of groups (with trivial edge groups for CTs). In this post I want to talk a little about how to think about train track maps and (“tame” in some sense) homotopy equivalences of graphs of groups more generally. At the end of the post I talk through using the train track algorithm to compute an example coming from a pseudo-Anosov 5-braid.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Axiom Of Choice Is False For Manifolds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/The-Axiom-of-Choice-is-False-for-Manifolds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Axiom Of Choice Is False For Manifolds" /><published>2020-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/The-Axiom-of-Choice-is-False-for-Manifolds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/The-Axiom-of-Choice-is-False-for-Manifolds.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a post about one of those things that is really a case of category theory
cheekily playing with unhooking a signifier from what it typically signifies.
Namely, one of the (many) tricky foundational things about working with orbifolds
goes by the name “the axiom of choice is false for the category of smooth manifolds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to misinterpret the statement is to take it literally:
as undergraduate math majors learn, the axiom of choice says that given an infinite collection of sets,
you can always choose exactly one element of each set, even if the collection is infinite.
Therefore the statement “the axiom of choice is false for the category of smooth manifolds”
could reasonably be thought to mean “given a collection of smooth manifolds,
which are in particular sets with additional structure,
it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case that you can always choose a point in each manifold if the collection is sufficiently large.”
Of course, if we accept the axiom of choice 
(I do, since I like the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nielsen–Schreier_theorem#Axiomatic_foundations&quot;&gt;Nielsen–Schreier theorem&lt;/a&gt;
which says that subgroups of free groups are free), 
then this statement is nonsense: it doesn’t matter if the collection of sets is really a collection of manifolds
or a collection of the contents of various grocery stores, we can always choose one element from each.
What, then, does this statement mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, there are two statements equivalent to the axiom of choice that have category-theoretic import.
This post is primarily concerned with the latter, but the former is too cute to pass up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;every-epimorphism-splits&quot;&gt;Every Epimorphism Splits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set theory is kind of in an odd position within mathematics.
I read some complaint that most mathematicians see sets every day
and yet have never seen sets be &lt;em&gt;interesting,&lt;/em&gt; 
and so discount the possibility that set theory could be a worthwhile pursuit.
The standard formulation of set theory as a foundation for mathematics is somewhat unfortunate, too:
if we take the axioms of Zermelo–Frankel set theory too literally, then we notice that everything is a set,
even the elements of sets.
Thus nonsensical questions like “what are the elements of 6” are allowable on a technicality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned this complaint, and everything in this section, from a beautiful 8-page article by Tom Leinster called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1212.6543.pdf&quot;&gt;“Rethinking Set Theory”&lt;/a&gt; from which I’d like to quote most of the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mathematicians manipulate sets with confidence almost every day, rarely making mistakes. 
Few of us, however, could accurately quote what are often referred to as “the” axioms of set theory. 
This suggests that we all carry around with us, perhaps subconsciously, 
a reliable body of operating principles for manipulating sets. 
What if we were to take some of those principles and adopt them as our axioms instead? 
The message of this article is that this can be done, in a simple, practical way (due to Lawvere). 
The resulting axioms are ten thoroughly mundane statements about sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these axioms, the formulation of the axiom of choice is perhaps the most devastatingly simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.&lt;/strong&gt; Every [surjective function of sets] has a right inverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see that this is really equivalent, notice that if \(p\colon S \to T\) is a surjective function of sets,
then we may identify \(S\) with the disjoint union&lt;/p&gt;

\[\coprod_{t \in T} p^{-1}(t).\]

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;right inverse&lt;/em&gt; for the function \(p\) is a function \(i \colon T \to S\)
such that \(p(i(t)) = t\) for all \(t\) in \(T\).
Notice that this means that \(i\colon T \to S\) picks out one element of \(p^{-1}(t)\) as \(t\)
varies over the elements of \(T\),
so the existence of such a function is equivalent to being able to perform choice in the sense that we said above!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This axiom can be reformulated in any category:
the correct generalization of a surjective function is called an &lt;em&gt;epimorphism;&lt;/em&gt;
for categories of “sets with additional structure” (e.g. groups, rings, manifolds) the surjective maps 
are epimorphisms, but the converse is not always true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A right inverse for an arrow \(f\colon c \to d\) makes sense in any category:
it’s an arrow \(r \colon d \to c\) such that \(fr\) is the identity arrow of \(c\).
It’s a general fact that admitting a right inverse implies that the arrow is an epimorphism,
even though we haven’t defined what that is.
In fact, for categories of “sets with additional structure” if \(f\) admits a right inverse,
then it is surjective.
We say \(f\) is a &lt;em&gt;split epimorphism&lt;/em&gt; (the name comes from “split exact sequences” of e.g. groups).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to cheekily reformulate the axiom of choice in any category as the following statement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Axiom of Choice for a Category:&lt;/strong&gt; every epimorphism is split.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This axiom fails for smooth manifolds:
a surjective map from the real line to the unit circle in \(\mathbb R^2\) given by sending \(x\)
to \((\cos x,\sin x)\) for instance, fails to have a right inverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-equivalent-definition-of-equivalence-of-categories&quot;&gt;An Equivalent Definition of Equivalence of Categories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another use of the axiom of choice in category theory is the following theorem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt; A functor \(F\colon C \to D\) between categories \(C\) and \(D\) is an &lt;em&gt;equivalence of categories&lt;/em&gt;
if and only if it is &lt;em&gt;fully faithful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;essentially surjective.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the functor \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;full&lt;/em&gt; if for all objects \(c\) and \(c'\) in \(C\), the function
\(F\colon C(c,c') \to D(Fc,Fc')\) is surjective, and &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; if it is injective.
So \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;fully faithful&lt;/em&gt; if it induces a bijection from the set of arrows betwwen any two objects in \(C\)
to their images in \(D\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functor \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;essentially surjective&lt;/em&gt; if every object \(d \in D\) is isomorphic to \(Fc\) for some
\(c \in C\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally an &lt;em&gt;equivalence of categories&lt;/em&gt; is a functor \(F\colon C \to D\) such that there exists an “inverse”
functor \(G \colon D \to C\) and natural isomorphisms between the two double compositions and the
identity functors of \(C\) and \(D\), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof that an equivalence of categories has the above properties is fairly simple: in an alternate universe,
this blog post would give it, and show that the converse requires the axiom of choice.
Let me just content myself with pointing out that the use of the axiom of choice is to pick
a \(c\) such that \(Fc\) is isomorphic to \(d\) for all \(d \in D\).
In fact, it turns out that the theorem is &lt;em&gt;equivalent&lt;/em&gt; to the axiom of choice,
if you make the appropriate definitions of the categories involved.
(e.g. \(D\) should be an index set, and \(C\) a clever category based on a collection
of sets indexed by \(D\).)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can define (small) categories &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; to a category and 
do category theory in this way. Thus one way to phrase the axiom of choice for a category is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Axiom of Choice for a Category:&lt;/strong&gt; A functor between categories internal to \(C\)
is an equivalence if and only if it is fully faithful and essentially surjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the category of smooth manifolds &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; fails this axiom,
essentially because it fails the previous one!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a post about one of those things that is really a case of category theory cheekily playing with unhooking a signifier from what it typically signifies. Namely, one of the (many) tricky foundational things about working with orbifolds goes by the name “the axiom of choice is false for the category of smooth manifolds.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Sheafy Adjunction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/26/A-Sheafy-Adjunction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Sheafy Adjunction" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/26/A-Sheafy-Adjunction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/26/A-Sheafy-Adjunction.html">&lt;p&gt;Given a topological space \(X\) and a continuous map \(\pi\colon X \to Y\),
there is an adjunction between the categories of sheaves on \(X\) and sheaves on \(Y\).
The adjunction is somewhat mysterious to me as I begin to write this,
so the hope is that by writing about it, I’ll begin to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functors in question are the &lt;em&gt;pushforward&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;inverse image&lt;/em&gt; functors,
which arise naturally in algebraic geometry (so I am led to believe).
What makes the adjunction difficult to understand is that the definitions
of the functors in question don’t seem to play nicely with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof (with a little setting the stage) appears below.
The method of proof, like most category-theoretic proofs,
is a story of careful bookkeeping with functors and natural transformations,
along with simple calculations to check.
The idea essentially seems to be that the 
unit \(\eta_\mathscr{F} \colon \mathscr{F} \to \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}\)
“shreds a section \(f\) into pieces,” while the counit
\(\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}} \colon \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}\)
recognizes that these “shredded up” sections assemble into sections of \(\mathscr{G}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adjunctions&quot;&gt;Adjunctions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, given categories \(C\) and \(D\), a pair of functors
\(F \colon C \to D\) and \(G \colon D \to C\) form an &lt;em&gt;adjoint pair&lt;/em&gt;
when there exists an isomorphism&lt;/p&gt;

\[D(Fc,d) \cong C(c,Gd)\]

&lt;p&gt;which is natural in \(c\) and \(d\).
We say \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;left adjoint&lt;/em&gt; to \(G\),
or equivalently that \(G\) is &lt;em&gt;right adjoint&lt;/em&gt; to \(F\).
In particular, setting \(d = Fc\), we have&lt;/p&gt;

\[D(Fc,Fc) \cong C(c,GFc).\]

&lt;p&gt;which gives us a natural transformation \(\eta \colon 1_C \Longrightarrow GF\).
Similarly, we have \(\epsilon\colon FG \Longrightarrow 1_D\).
The natural transformation \(\eta\) is called the &lt;em&gt;unit&lt;/em&gt; of the adjunction,
and \(\epsilon\) is the &lt;em&gt;counit.&lt;/em&gt;
In fact, the existence of these natural transformations
could be taken to be the &lt;em&gt;definition&lt;/em&gt; of an adjunction,
provided the natural transformations satisfy the identities&lt;/p&gt;

\[\epsilon F \circ F\eta = 1_F \quad\text{and}\quad G\epsilon \circ \eta G = 1_G,\]

&lt;p&gt;which says that for all \(c \in C\) and \(d \in D\), the compositions&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}
\begin{CD}
Fc @&amp;gt;{F\eta_c}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; FGFc @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{Fc}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Fc
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
Gd @&amp;gt;{\eta_{Gd}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; GFGd @&amp;gt;{G\epsilon_d}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Gd
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;are the identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal in this blog post is to show that the functors I am interested in
satisfy this latter definition of an adjunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheaves&quot;&gt;Sheaves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a pair of spaces \(X\) and \(Y\), and a continuous map \(\pi \colon X \to Y\),
we have functors \(\pi_\ast \colon \operatorname{Sh}_X \to \operatorname{Sh}_Y\)
and \(\pi^{-1}\colon \operatorname {Sh}_Y \to \operatorname{Sh}_X\) from the category
of sheaves on \(X\) to the category of sheaves on \(Y\) and &lt;em&gt;vice versa.&lt;/em&gt;
The former is simple to describe: if \(\mathscr{G}\) is a sheaf on \(X\),
the &lt;em&gt;pushforward sheaf&lt;/em&gt; \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\) on \(Y\) is the assignment&lt;/p&gt;

\[U \mapsto \mathscr{F}(\pi^{-1}(U))\]

&lt;p&gt;for all open subsets \(U\) of \(Y\).
If \(\psi \colon \mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\) is a morphism of sheaves on \(X\),
the morphism \(\pi_\ast\psi\) is defined by the rule&lt;/p&gt;

\[(\pi_\ast\psi)(U) = \psi(\pi^{-1}(U)).\]

&lt;p&gt;The latter is slightly more complicated.
Recall that if \(\mathscr{F}\) is a sheaf on \(Y\),
there is a space \(F\) equipped with a local homeomorphism \(\rho \colon F \to Y\).
The sheaf \(\mathscr{F}\) is the sheaf of local sections of \(\rho\);
\(F\) is called the &lt;em&gt;espace étale&lt;/em&gt; for the sheaf \(\mathscr{F}\).
The set of points of \(F\) above \(y \in Y\) is the &lt;em&gt;stalk&lt;/em&gt; \(\mathscr{F}_y\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, a section \(s\colon U \to F\) of the projection \(\rho \colon F \to X\)
is an element \((s_y)_{y \in U}\) of \(\prod_{y \in U} \mathscr{F}_y\).
In our case, continuity of \(s\) is the following condition&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}\label{star}\tag{$\ast$}
\text{for all } y \in U, \text{ there exists an open neighborhood }
U_y \text{ of } y\\  \text{ and } f\in\mathscr{F}(U_y) \text{ such that }
f_x = s_x \text{ for all } x \in U_y.
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Given that \(F\) and \(X\) admit maps to \(Y\), we can form their pullback,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi^{-1}F @&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; F \\
@VVV @VV{\rho}V \\
X @&amp;gt;{\pi}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Y
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;which as a set is  \(\{ (x,f_y) \in X \times F : \pi(x) = y\}\).
The topology on \(\pi^{-1}F\) is induced from the product topology on \(X \times F\).
The &lt;em&gt;inverse image sheaf&lt;/em&gt; \(\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}\) is the sheaf of sections of \(\pi^{-1}F \to X\).
The universal property of the pullback ensures that this really defines a functor
from the category of sheaves on \(Y\) to the category of sheaves on \(X\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Condition \(\eqref{star}\) for continuity of a section \(s\colon V \to \pi^{-1}F\)—that is,
a tuple \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) in \(\prod_{x \in V}\mathscr{F}_{\pi(x)}\)—says
that for all \(x \in V\) there exists an open neighborhood \(V_x\) of \(x\)
and an open neighborhood \(U_x\) in \(Y\) such that \(\pi(V_x) \subset U_x\).
Furthermore there exists a section \(f \in \mathscr{F}(U_x)\) 
such that \(f_{\pi(v)} = s_{\pi(v)}\) for all \(v \in V_x\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(\phi\colon \mathscr{F} \to \mathscr{F}'\) is a morphism of sheaves on \(Y\),
the resulting morphism \(\pi^{-1}\phi \colon \pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} \to \pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}'\)
is defined by&lt;/p&gt;

\[(\pi^{-1}\phi)(V)\left[(s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\right] = \left(\phi_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in V}.\]

&lt;p&gt;One needs to demonstrate that the right-hand side satisfies condition \(\eqref{star}\);
the check is simple, so I’ll leave it to the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim is that \(\pi^{-1}\) is left adjoint to \(\pi_\ast\).
Therefore we should expect natural transformations
\(\eta \colon 1_{\operatorname{Sh}_Y} \Longrightarrow \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\)
and \(\epsilon \colon \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast \Longrightarrow 1_{\operatorname{Sh}_X}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-unit-of-the-adjunction&quot;&gt;The Unit of the Adjunction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let \(\mathscr{F}\) be a sheaf on \(Y\),
and let \(U\) be an open set in \(Y\).
Since \(\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U) = \pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(\pi^{-1}(U))\),
we can think of \(s \in \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U)\) as
a section \(s \colon \pi^{-1}(U) \to \pi^{-1}F\),
i.e. a tuple \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)}\)
satisfying the compatibility condition above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in particular if \(U \subset Y\) is open
and \(f \in \mathscr{F}(U)\), the continuity condition \(\eqref{star}\)
for a section \(\pi^{-1}(U)\to \pi^{-1}F\) is satisfied by the section
\((f_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)}\),
and thus defines an element of \(\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us thus define a map \(\eta_{\mathscr{F}}(U)\colon \mathscr{F}(U) \to \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U)\) 
as&lt;/p&gt;

\[\eta_{\mathscr{F}}(U)(f) = (f_{\pi(x)})_{x\in\pi^{-1}(U)}.\]

&lt;p&gt;(Let’s parse the notation: a natural transformation \(\eta\) yields
a map of sheaves \(\eta_{\mathscr{F}}\) for each sheaf \(\mathscr{F}\).
This is the definition of that map on the open subset \(U \subset Y\).)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prove the claim that \(\eta\) is a natural transformation,
we need to show that given a map \(\phi \colon \mathscr{F} \to \mathscr{F}'\)
of sheaves on \(Y\), the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\mathscr{F} @&amp;gt;{\eta_{\mathscr{F}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} \\
@V{\phi}VV @VV{\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\phi}V \\
\mathscr{F}' @&amp;gt;{\eta_{\mathscr{F}'}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}'.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Given \(f \in \mathscr{F}(U)\), commutativity of the square is the claim that
the following equality holds&lt;/p&gt;

\[\left((\phi(U)(f))_{\pi(x)}\right)_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)} 
= \left(\phi_{\pi(x)}(f_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)}.\]

&lt;p&gt;This is in fact true, since taking the stalk at \(x\) is functorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-counit-of-the-adjunction&quot;&gt;The Counit of the Adjunction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now suppose that \(\mathscr{G}\) is a sheaf on \(X\).
Let \(\pi_\ast G\) denote the &lt;em&gt;espace étale&lt;/em&gt; over \(Y\) for the sheaf \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A section \(s \colon V \to \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast G\)
is a tuple \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) taking values in \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}_{\pi(x)}\)
satisfying the continuity condition \(\eqref{star}\),
which in our particular case asserts the existence,
for each \(x \in V\), of an open neighborhood \(V_x\) of \(x\) and an open neighborhood
\(U_x\) in \(Y\) satisfying \(\pi(V_x) \subset U_x\).
Furthermore there exists \(g \in \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U_x) = \mathscr{G}(\pi^{-1}(U_x))\)
such that the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\) in \(\mathscr{G}_x\) under the natural map
\(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}_{\pi(x)} \to \mathscr{G}_x\) is equal to \(g_x\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the sets \(\pi^{-1}(U_x)\) cover \(V\) by assumption,
sheafiness of \(\mathscr{G}\) implies the existence of a unique \(g \in \mathscr{G}(V)\)
such that \(g_x\) is equal to the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\)
under the natural map \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}_{\pi(x)} \to \mathscr{G}_x\)
for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; \(x \in V\).
Let us thus define a map \(\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}}(V) \colon \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(V) \to \mathscr{G}(V)\)
sending \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x\in V}\) to \(g\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We claim that \(\epsilon\) defines a natural transformation from \(\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\) to \(\mathscr{G}\).
To prove the claim, we need to show that given a map \(\psi\colon \mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\)
of sheaves on \(X\), the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G} @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \mathscr{G} \\
@V{\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\psi}VV @VV{\psi}V \\
\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast \mathscr{G}' @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}'}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \mathscr{G}'.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Given \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V} \in \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(V)\),
the upper right path of the square sends us first to some \(g \in \mathscr{G}(V)\)
such that \(g_x\) is the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\) in \(\mathscr{G}_x\) for all \(x \in V\),
and then sends \(g\) to \(\psi(V)(g) \in \mathscr{G}'(V)\).
On the other hand, the lower left path of the square sends
\((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) first to \(\left((\pi_\ast\psi)_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in V}\)
in \(\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}'(V)\), and then to
some \(g' \in \mathscr{G}'(V)\) such that \(g'_x\) is the image of
\((\pi_\ast\psi)_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\) in \(\mathscr{G}'_x\) for all \(x \in V\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(U \subset Y\) is an open set containing \(\pi(x)\) such that
\(s \in \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U) = \mathscr{G}(\pi^{-1}(U))\) 
represents \(s_{\pi(x)}\) for \(\pi(x) \in U\),
we have \((\pi_\ast\psi)_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)}) = \psi(\pi^{-1}(U))(s)_{\pi(x)}\).
Furthermore we know that \(g \in \mathscr{G}(V)\) 
is such that the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\) in \(\mathscr{G}_x\)
is \(g_x\) for all \(x \in V\).
Therefore we have that
the image of \(\psi(\pi^{-1}(U))(s)_{\pi(x)}\)
in \(\mathscr{G}'_x\) is equal to \(\psi(V)(g)_x\),
as desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-inverse-imagepushforward-adjunction&quot;&gt;The inverse image–pushforward adjunction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, we just need to show that two double compositions
of natural transformations are the identity.
The first, translated into our particular case,
says that if \(\mathscr{F}\) is a sheaf on \(Y\),
we have that&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} @&amp;gt;{\pi^{-1}\eta_{\mathscr{F}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;is equal to the identity.
The difficulty here seems to be largely notational.
Let \(V \subset X\) be an open set.
Suppose \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) is a section in \(\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(V)\).
We have&lt;/p&gt;

\[(\pi^{-1}\eta_{\mathscr{F}})(V)\left[(s_{\pi(x)})_{x\in V}\right]
= \left((\eta_{\mathscr{F}})_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in V}
\in \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(V).\]

&lt;p&gt;First observe that the continuity condition \(\eqref{star}\) tells us that
there is, for each \(x \in V\), an open neighborhood \(V_x\) of \(x\) and
an open set \(U_x \subset Y\) containing \(\pi(V_x)\).
On this open set we have \(s \in \mathscr{F}(U_x)\) such that
\(\left((\eta_{\mathscr{F}})(U_x)(s)\right)_{\pi(x)} = (\eta_{\mathscr{F}})_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw above that \((\eta_{\mathscr{F}})(U_x)(s)\) is the section
\((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U_x)} \in \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U_x) = 
\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(\pi^{-1}(U))\).
The map \(\epsilon_{\pi^{-1}\mathscr F}\) recognizes that the sections
\((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U_x)}\) satisfy the compatibility conditions
to glue up to form a section \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) in \(\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(V)\),
demonstrating that the double composition is indeed the identity. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second double composition we need to show is equal to the identity is defined 
for a sheaf \(\mathscr{G}\) on \(X\) as follows&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi_\ast\mathscr{G} @&amp;gt;{\eta_{\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}
@&amp;gt;{\pi_\ast\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;If \(U \subset Y\) is an open set and \(g \in \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U)\)
is a section,
the first map sends \(g\) to the section
\((g_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)} \in \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second map recognizes that the above section and \(g \in \mathscr{G}(\pi^{-1}(U)) = \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\)
agree on each stalk, and so sends our section back to \(g\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This completes the proof that inverse image and pushforward form an adjoint pair of functors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Given a topological space \(X\) and a continuous map \(\pi\colon X \to Y\), there is an adjunction between the categories of sheaves on \(X\) and sheaves on \(Y\). The adjunction is somewhat mysterious to me as I begin to write this, so the hope is that by writing about it, I’ll begin to understand.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two Approaches To The Cotangent Space</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/Two-Approaches-to-the-Cotangent-Space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two Approaches To The Cotangent Space" /><published>2020-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/Two-Approaches-to-the-Cotangent-Space</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/Two-Approaches-to-the-Cotangent-Space.html">&lt;p&gt;There is a “sheaf-theoretic” definition of something like a &lt;em&gt;cotangent space at a point&lt;/em&gt;
for a locally-ringed space.
In the case of the sheaf of differentiable functions on a smooth manifold,
the two definitions—sheaf-theoretic and the usual one in differential geometry—agree.
What’s more, modulo the appropriate background technology in both subjects,
the proof is beautiful and simple—I feel like shouting it from the rooftops
at the moment, so this blog post will try and give a little exposition.
I’ll try to move briskly without assuming total familiarity with either side of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-algebraic-cotangent-space&quot;&gt;The Algebraic Cotangent Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let \(X\) be a smooth manifold of dimension \(n\).
The &lt;em&gt;sheaf&lt;/em&gt; of differentiable functions on \(X\) is a
contravariant functor from the category of open subsets of \(X\) to the category of rings
that assigns to an open set \(U\)
the ring \(\mathscr{O}(U)\) of differentiable functions \(f\colon U \to \mathbb{R}\)—addition
and multiplication in \(\mathscr{O}(U)\) are done pointwise in \(\mathbb{R}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sheaf is not so important for us;
what we are interested in today are the &lt;em&gt;stalks.&lt;/em&gt;
The idea is that elements of the &lt;em&gt;stalk,&lt;/em&gt;
called &lt;em&gt;germs,&lt;/em&gt; capture the “infinitesimal behavior”
of smooth functions at a point.
Here is the formal definition.
Given a point \(p \in X\), 
the &lt;em&gt;stalk&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;germs&lt;/em&gt; of smooth functions at \(p\) is the ring&lt;/p&gt;

\[\mathscr{O}_p = \{(f,U) : f \in \mathscr{O}(U),\ p\in U \}/\sim.\]

&lt;p&gt;The equivalence relation \(\sim\) is defined as follows:
we say \((f,U) \sim (g,V)\) if there exists an open neighborhood
\(U' \subset U \cap V\) such that \(f|_{U'} = g|_{U'}\).
The equivalence class of \((f,U)\) is its &lt;em&gt;germ.&lt;/em&gt;
The ring \(\mathscr{O}_p\) is the direct limit of the \(\mathscr{O}(U)\)
as \(U\) varies over the open neighborhoods of \(p\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that there is a surjection \(\mathscr{O}_p \to \mathbb{R}\)
that sends the germ of \(f\) at \(p\) to \(f(p)\in \mathbb{R}\).
The definition is independent of the choice of representative \(f\).
Since \(\mathbb{R}\) is a field, the kernel of the map
is a maximal ideal; let’s call it \(\mathfrak{m}_p\).
Observe that 
\(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2\) is a module over
\(\mathscr{O}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p \cong \mathbb{R}\), 
i.e. a real vector space;
we will call it the &lt;em&gt;algebraic cotangent space at \(p\).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-usual-cotangent-space&quot;&gt;The Usual Cotangent Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We retain our manifold \(X\) and point \(p\) from the previous section.
The &lt;em&gt;tangent space at \(p\),&lt;/em&gt; denoted \(T_pX\)
can be thought of as the space of “directions” in \(X\) at \(p\).
This is made precise by defining it to be the space of
directional &lt;em&gt;derivatives&lt;/em&gt; at \(p\).
I won’t attempt to make this more precise, except to note that
after we choose local coordinates \((x_1,\dotsc,x_n)\) near \(p = (p_1,\dotsc,p_n)\),
a basis for \(T_pX\) is given by&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{\partial}{\partial x_1}\bigg|_p,\dotsc, \frac{\partial}{\partial x_n}\bigg|_p.\]

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;cotangent space,&lt;/em&gt; which we are more interested in, is the
&lt;em&gt;dual&lt;/em&gt; of the tangent space and is denoted \(T_p^\ast X\).
Elements of the cotangent space are &lt;em&gt;linear functionals&lt;/em&gt; on tangent vectors.
Given coordinates \(x_1,\dotsc,x_n\),
the &lt;em&gt;dual basis&lt;/em&gt; of the cotangent space is given by&lt;/p&gt;

\[dx_1,\dotsc, dx_n,\]

&lt;p&gt;so we have \(dx_i\left( \frac{\partial}{\partial x_j}|_p\right)\) equal to \(1\)
when \(i = j\) and equal to \(0\) otherwise.
(There perhaps ought to be some notational inclusion of the point \(p\),
but we will suppress this.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-algebraic-cotangent-space-agrees-with-the-usual-one&quot;&gt;The Algebraic Cotangent Space Agrees With the Usual One&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(f\) is a smooth function on an open neighborhood of \(p\)
satisfying \(f(p) = 0\),
abusing notation, we shall write the corresponding element of
\(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2\)
as \(f + \mathfrak{m}_p^2\).
Given such an element,
I claim we can interpret \(f\) as a linear functional on tangent vectors at \(p\)
by sending a tangent vector \(v\) to the value of the derivative of \(f\) at \(p\) in the direction \(v\).
For instance, in local coordinates \((x_1,\dotsc,x_n)\),
the vector \(\frac{\partial}{\partial x_i}|_p\) is sent to \(\frac{\partial f}{\partial x_i}(p)\).
Extending linearly defines a linear functional on \(T_pX\),
which we shall denote \(df_p\).
The value of the directional derivative of a function depends only on its germ
essentially by definition,
and the product rule from calculus tells us that the assignment
\(f \mapsto df_p\) sends elements of \(\mathfrak{m}_p^2\) to the zero functional.
The linearity of the derivative implies that \(\mathbb{R}\)-linear combinations
of germs are sent to \(\mathbb{R}\)-linear combinations of functionals,
so the assignment&lt;/p&gt;

\[f + \mathfrak{m}_p^2 \mapsto df_p\]

&lt;p&gt;really defines a map \(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 \to T_p^\ast X\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We claim this map is an isomorphism, for which it suffices to define an inverse.
Choose local coordinates \(\vec x = (x_1,\dotsc,x_n)\) around \(\vec p = (p_1,\dotsc,p_n)\).
A general element \(\alpha\) of \(T_p^\ast X\)
may be written as the linear combination
\(\alpha = a_1\mathop{dx_1} + \dotsb + a_n\mathop{dx_n}.\)
Write \(\vec a = (a_1,\dotsc,a_n)\).
The function \(f_\alpha\) defined as&lt;/p&gt;

\[f_\alpha(\vec x) = \vec a\cdot(\vec x - \vec p)\]

&lt;p&gt;clearly has germ belonging to \(\mathfrak{m}_p\),
and tracing the double composition,
we see that we have \(a \mapsto f_\alpha + \mathfrak{m}_p^2 \mapsto d(f_\alpha)_p = \alpha\).
This map will be an isomorphism as soon as we can show that the germ of
\(f - f_{df_p}\) belongs to \(\mathfrak{m}_p^2\), i.e.
can be written as \(g_1h_1 + \dotsb g_kh_k\) for some
smooth functions \(g_i\) and \(h_i\) whose germs belong to \(\mathfrak{m}_p\).
This is the statement of Taylor’s theorem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even better, the map \(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 \to T_p^\ast X\)
is a &lt;em&gt;natural isomorphism,&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that given a smooth map
\(\varphi\colon X \to Y\) of smooth manifolds such that
\(\varphi(p) = q\), the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}
	\begin{CD}
		\mathfrak{m}_q/\mathfrak{m}_q^2 @&amp;gt;{\cong}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; T_q^\ast Y \\
		@VV{\varphi^\ast}V @VV{\varphi^\ast}V \\
		\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 @&amp;gt;{\cong}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; T_p^\ast X.
	\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;To verify this, we shall follow an element \(f + \mathfrak{m}_q^2\)
around the diagram&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
		f + \mathfrak{m}^2_q @&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; df_q \\
		@VVV @VVV \\
		f\varphi + \mathfrak{m}_p^2 @&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d(f\varphi)_p = \mathop{df_q}\mathop{d\varphi_p},
	\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;and the fact that equality holds is the multi-variable chain rule!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having exploited our knowledge of undegraduate calculus to prove a satisfying
natural isomorphism,
I’ll leave you with one final reason this proof excites me.
If we had wanted to, we could have replaced “differentiable” with “continuous”
in our definition of the algebraic cotangent space,
and we would still end up with a real vector space associated to every stalk.
In some sense, I guessed that this says that the only reason one never speaks of a (co)tangent
space associated to a point in a general topological space is that
there’s no reason—like Taylor’s theorem—for the space to be finite-dimensional!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the truth is slightly more subtle:
every continuous function has a continuous “square root” in the sense
that we can always write \(f(x) = \operatorname{sgn}(f(x))\sqrt{f(x)}\sqrt{f(x)}\),
and the functions \(\sqrt{f}\) and \(\operatorname{sgn}(f)\sqrt(f)\) are continuous.
Therefore it is \(\mathfrak{m}_p\) that is infinite-dimensional,
while \(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 = 0\).
(Thanks to Curtis Heberle and Christopher Davis for pointing out my error!)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There is a “sheaf-theoretic” definition of something like a cotangent space at a point for a locally-ringed space. In the case of the sheaf of differentiable functions on a smooth manifold, the two definitions—sheaf-theoretic and the usual one in differential geometry—agree. What’s more, modulo the appropriate background technology in both subjects, the proof is beautiful and simple—I feel like shouting it from the rooftops at the moment, so this blog post will try and give a little exposition. I’ll try to move briskly without assuming total familiarity with either side of things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Orbifolds Day One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/05/Orbifolds-Day-One.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Orbifolds Day One" /><published>2020-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/05/Orbifolds-Day-One</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/05/Orbifolds-Day-One.html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/OrbifoldNotes1.pdf&quot;&gt;some notes&lt;/a&gt; introducing orbifolds from Haefliger’s perspective in &lt;em&gt;Metric Spaces of Non-positive Curvature&lt;/em&gt;.
There is some surprisingly heavy machinery that goes into it.
In this blog post I want to talk a little about it at a high level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;orbifold&lt;/em&gt; of dimension \(n\) is a Hausdorff space locally modeled on \(\mathbb{R}^n\) modulo
the action of a finite group.
This is a simple enough idea on its face:
a useful perspective on the fundamental group of a manifold 
is the passage between its action on the universal cover
and the calculus of loops in the base space.
For a group \(G\) that acts merely properly discontinuously and not freely,
the quotient space is no longer a manifold,
and yet we would like to accesss the “loops” perspective regardless.
This is the idea that orbifolds are trying to capture.
It is maybe surprising both how successful this project is,
and yet how much more complex the theory becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s remember back to when we learned Calculus.
First we learned how to manipulate real-valued functions of one variable,
and later multivariable functions \(f\colon \mathbb{R}^m \to \mathbb{R}^n\).
In particular, we defined a notion of differentiability for these maps.
To replicate this effort on differentiable manifolds,
one uses &lt;em&gt;charts.&lt;/em&gt; The idea is that the local structure of a manifold \(M\)
can be captured by a map \(\varphi\colon U \to M\), where \(U\) is an
open subset of \(\mathbb{R}^n\).
A map of manifolds \(f\colon M \to N\) is &lt;em&gt;defined&lt;/em&gt; to be differentiable
if its expression in any pair of charts is differentiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ridiculously maximalist approach to this idea is the following:
suppose \((U_i,\varphi_i)_{i\in I}\) is an &lt;em&gt;atlas&lt;/em&gt; for \(M\)
(in the usual sense), and that \((V_j,\psi_j)_{j\in J}\)
is an atlas for \(N\).
A function \(f\colon M \to N\)
defines a map \(f_{ij}\colon U_i \to V_j\)
whenever \(f\varphi_i(U_i) \subset \psi_j(V_j)\).
By refining the open cover of \(M\), we can assume this is always the case.
We can do the following strange thing:
the disjoint union \(U = \coprod_{i\in I}U_i\)
is a differentiable manifold, each of whose components is an open subset of \(\mathbb{R}^m\),
and the resulting map \(\varphi = \coprod_{i\in I}\varphi_i\) is differentiable
(in fact a local diffeomorphism).
The maps \(f_{ij}\) assemble into a map \(F\colon U \to V\) such that the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}\begin{CD} U @&amp;gt;F&amp;gt;&amp;gt; V \\ @VV\varphi V @VV\psi V \\ M @&amp;gt;f&amp;gt;&amp;gt; N. \end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;And we are justified in saying that \(f\) is differentiable when there exists
a map \(F\) constructed as above.
What we have done, essentially, is said that we don’t understand the quotient manifold,
but we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; understand open subsets of \(\mathbb{R}^m\), and have performed
a non-unique but useful construction to exploit that understanding.
This is the jumping-off point for orbifolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is just one more wrinkle: 
the definition of an atlas includes various differentiable maps
called &lt;em&gt;changes of charts.&lt;/em&gt; It would be convenient if there
were a way to stipulate that our map \(F\) must play nicely with these changes of charts
beyond just saying that there exists a map on the quotient space.
This is where Lie Groupoids come in: they turn out to be precisely the gadget we need
to manage the expression of \(f\) in charts while asserting that these expressions
play nicely with the changes of charts.
I’ll let you read the notes—and Haefliger too, hopefully.
Next time I’ll try to wrap my head around the fundamental group of an orbifold,
and hopefully thereafter the mapping class group of an orbifold.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I wrote some notes introducing orbifolds from Haefliger’s perspective in Metric Spaces of Non-positive Curvature. There is some surprisingly heavy machinery that goes into it. In this blog post I want to talk a little about it at a high level.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Category Theory Day One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/16/Category-Theory-Day-One.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Category Theory Day One" /><published>2020-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/16/Category-Theory-Day-One</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/16/Category-Theory-Day-One.html">&lt;p&gt;My office-mate asked me to give a “second lecture” in category theory
in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.danielkeliher.com/EminarCurrent.html&quot;&gt;Eminar&lt;/a&gt;, the Tufts graduate student seminar. I gave a first lecture
last semester, but I thought it might be nice to have something to point people
who missed it to, in order to stick to my assignment
and begin at the Yoneda lemma. So, here is yet another rendition of the first
hour of a category theory class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treatment is brisk. To the interested reader,
I would highly recommend Emily Riehl’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.jhu.edu/~eriehl/context.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Category Theory in Context&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
which is the main inspiration here and
has the advantage of being available on the author’s website.
I also recommend Saunders Mac Lane’s 
&lt;em&gt;Category Theory for the Working Mathematician&lt;/em&gt;
and Francis Borceux’s &lt;em&gt;Handbook of Categorical Algebra.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;categories&quot;&gt;Categories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;category&lt;/em&gt; \(C\) is a collection of &lt;em&gt;objects,&lt;/em&gt; say \(c\), \(d\), and 
&lt;em&gt;arrows&lt;/em&gt; between them, say \(f\colon c\to d\).
Given a pair of arrows as below&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}\begin{CD} a @&amp;gt;f&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b @&amp;gt;g&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c,\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;we require the existence of their &lt;em&gt;composition,&lt;/em&gt; \(gf\colon a\to c\).
Composition is associative, and for each object \(c\), there is a
(unique) arrow \(1_c\colon c\to c\) which acts as an identity for composition
of arrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many familiar mathematical objects assemble into categories.
To wit, there is the &lt;em&gt;category of sets,&lt;/em&gt; where objects are sets
and arrows are functions of sets, and the &lt;em&gt;category of topological spaces,&lt;/em&gt;
where objects are topological spaces and arrows are continuous maps.
However, the notion of a category is flexible: not all categories
have “sets with additional structure” as objects.
For instance, a &lt;em&gt;preorder&lt;/em&gt; is the same data as a category
where there is at most one arrow between any two objects.
Here an arrow \(c\to d\) should be interpreted as saying \(c\le d\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I use the term &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt; advisedly: Russell’s paradox
says that there can be no set of all sets, so the category of
sets has more than a set’s worth of objects! However,
between any two sets, there is only a set’s worth of distinct functions.
That is, if \(a\) and \(b\) are sets, there is a &lt;em&gt;set&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

\[\operatorname{Set}(a,b) = \{f\colon a \to b\}.\]

&lt;p&gt;Categories where this is the case for all objects are called &lt;em&gt;locally small.&lt;/em&gt;
If additionally there is only a set’s worth of arrows in the entire category
(and thus only a set’s worth of objects!), the category is called &lt;em&gt;small.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;functors&quot;&gt;Functors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If \(C\) and \(D\) are categories, a &lt;em&gt;functor&lt;/em&gt; \(F\colon C \to D\)
is an assignment&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}a &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp;Fa \\ @VfVV \mapsto @VVFfV \\ b &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp;Fb.\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;I.e. for each object \(a\) of \(C\), there is an object \(Fa\) in \(D\),
and for each arrow \(f\colon a\to b\) in \(C\), there is an arrow
\(Ff\colon Fa\to Fb\). Additionally, \(F\) is required to satisfy&lt;/p&gt;

\[F1_{a} = 1_{Fa}\]

&lt;p&gt;for all \(a\) in \(C\), and \(F\) must
respect composition in the sense that&lt;/p&gt;

\[F(gf) = FgFf.\]

&lt;p&gt;Such functors are sometimes called &lt;em&gt;covariant.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every category \(C\) has an &lt;em&gt;opposite category&lt;/em&gt; 
\(\newcommand{\op}{^{\mathrm{op}}}C\op\), which is obtained from
formally reversing the direction of all the arrows.
Thus if \(C\) has arrows&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD} a @&amp;gt;f&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b @&amp;gt;g&amp;gt;&amp;gt; c,\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;then \(C\op\) has arrows&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD} a @&amp;lt;f\op&amp;lt;&amp;lt; b @&amp;lt;g\op&amp;lt;&amp;lt; c.\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Any statement about objects and arrows in \(C\) has a &lt;em&gt;dual&lt;/em&gt;
statement about objects and arrows in \(C\op\), which is obtained
by reversing the direction of all the arrows.
If the proof of the original statement is categorical,
dualizing the proof yields a proof of the dual statement for \(C\op\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of a functor admits dualization in \(C\) or in \(D\).
The import is essentially the same as long as only one dualization is
performed: the result is a &lt;em&gt;contravariant functor&lt;/em&gt; \(G\colon C\op \to D\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD} a &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp; Ga \\ @VfVV \mapsto @AAGfA \\ b &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp;Gb.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Functors abound in mathematics. Many are so simple that we hardly think about
them: for instance the “forgetful” 
functor from the category of groups and homomorphisms
to sets that sends a group \(G\) to its set of elements,
and a group homomorphism to its action on underlying sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(C\) is a locally small category and \(c\) is an object,
there are two particularly important functors \(C \to \operatorname{Set}\).
Write \(C(c,b)\) and \(C(b,c)\) for the set of arrows in \(C\)
with domain and codomain \(c\), respectively.
If \(f\colon b\to d\) is an arrow in \(C\), there are
functions&lt;/p&gt;

\[f_*\colon C(c,b) \to C(c,d) \text{ and }f^*\colon C(d,c) \to C(b,c)\]

&lt;p&gt;defined as \(f_*(g) = fg\) and \(f^*(h) = hf\), respectively.
The assignments&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD} b &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp; C(c,b) &amp;amp;\qquad\qquad &amp;amp;b &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp; C(b,c) \\
    @VfVV \mapsto @VVf_*V \qquad\qquad @VfVV \mapsto @AAf*A \\
    d &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp;C(c,d) &amp;amp;\qquad\qquad &amp;amp;d &amp;amp;\mapsto &amp;amp; C(d,c)
  \end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;define covariant and contravariant functors 
\(C(c,-)\colon C \to \operatorname{Set}\) and&lt;br /&gt;
\(C(-,c)\colon C\op\to\operatorname{Set}\), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;natural-transformations&quot;&gt;Natural Transformations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as we have defined functors between categories,
it is  useful to consider &lt;em&gt;functor categories,&lt;/em&gt;
whose elements are functors \(C\to D\). To do this, we need 
a  notion of a morphism between functors. It turns out
that the right notion is a &lt;em&gt;natural transformation.&lt;/em&gt;
If \(F,G\colon C \to D\) are functors, a natural transformation
\(\eta\colon F\Rightarrow G\) is a collection of maps
\(\eta_c\colon Fc \to Gc\), one for each object \(c\) of \(C\)
such that for every arrow \(f\colon c \to d\), the following
diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
  Fc @&amp;gt;\eta_c&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Gc \\
  @VFfVV @VVGfV \\
  Fd @&amp;gt;\eta_d&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Gd.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Any directed path in a diagram of objects and arrows within
a category like the above yields an arrow from the initial 
“vertex” of the path to the terminal one by reading off the
labelled arrows. A diagram &lt;em&gt;commutes&lt;/em&gt; if any two directed
paths with the same endpoints yield equal arrows.
Thus, to say that the above diagram commutes asserts the
equality&lt;/p&gt;

\[Gf\eta_c = \eta_d Ff.\]

&lt;p&gt;The standard example of a natural transformation is the following.
Let \(k\) be a field, and consider the category of \(k\)-vector spaces
and linear transformations. There is a contravariant functor
that sends a vector space \(V\) to its &lt;em&gt;dual&lt;/em&gt; \(V^*\), namely the vector
space of linear transformations \(V\to k\).
A linear map \(f\colon V \to W\) is sent to a map \(f^*\colon W^*\to V^*\)
which is defined as follows.
If \(\lambda\colon W \to k\) is an element of \(W^*\),
\(f^*(\lambda)\) is the linear  map&lt;/p&gt;

\[\lambda f\colon V\to k.\]

&lt;p&gt;Thus there is a &lt;em&gt;covariant&lt;/em&gt; functor sending a vector space \(V\)
to its “double dual” \(V^{**}=(V^*)^*\).
There is a natural transformation \(ev\) from the identity functor
to the double dual functor.
At a given vector space \(V\), the map \(ev_V\) sends a vector \(v\)
to the linear map \(V^*\to k\) defined by “evaluation at \(v\),”
namely&lt;/p&gt;

\[\lambda \mapsto \lambda(v),\quad  \lambda \in V^*.\]

&lt;p&gt;Naturality of \(ev\) asserts that for \(f\colon V \to W\)
a linear map, the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
  V @&amp;gt;ev_V&amp;gt;&amp;gt; V^{**} \\
  @VfVV @VVf^{**}V \\
  W @&amp;gt;ev_W&amp;gt;&amp;gt; W^{**}.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;To show this, consider a vector \(v \in V\).
The element \(f^{**}(ev_V(v)) \in W^{**}\) is
the linear map&lt;/p&gt;

\[ev_V(v)\circ f^*\colon W^*\to k,\]

&lt;p&gt;so its action on \(\lambda \in W*\) is&lt;/p&gt;

\[ev_V(v)(f^*(\lambda)) = ev_V(v)(\lambda f) = 
\lambda (f(v)) = ev_W(f(v))(\lambda),\]

&lt;p&gt;demonstrating naturality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map \(ev_V\) is an isomorphism when \(V\) is finite dimensional.
Thus we say that when restricted to the &lt;em&gt;subcategory&lt;/em&gt;
of finite dimensional vector spaces, \(ev\) is a &lt;em&gt;natural isomorphism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-yoneda-lemma&quot;&gt;The Yoneda Lemma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the fundamental result in category theory
is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem.&lt;/strong&gt; (The Yoneda Lemma)    &lt;br /&gt;
 Let \(C\) be a locally small category and
 \(F\colon C \to \operatorname{Set}\) a functor.
 For each object \(c\) of \(C\), there is a bijection&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

\[\{\alpha\colon C(c,-)\Rightarrow F\} \longleftrightarrow \{x \in Fc\}\]

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;implemented by sending a natural transformation
 \(\alpha\) to the element \(\alpha_c(1_c)\).
 This bijection is natural in \(F\) and \(c\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof is straightforward, once one figures out what needs proving.
The utility of the Yoneda lemma is likely 
far from obvious when one first meets it,
but it turns out to be a major tool in category theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My office-mate asked me to give a “second lecture” in category theory in Eminar, the Tufts graduate student seminar. I gave a first lecture last semester, but I thought it might be nice to have something to point people who missed it to, in order to stick to my assignment and begin at the Yoneda lemma. So, here is yet another rendition of the first hour of a category theory class.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choo Choo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/06/Choo-Choo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choo Choo" /><published>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/09/06/Choo-Choo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/06/Choo-Choo.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I posted my first paper, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.03097&quot;&gt;Train Tracks, Orbigraphs and CAT(0) Free-by-cyclic Groups&lt;/a&gt;
to the ArXiv! Here is a description of the paper and the idea behind the main application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;orbigraphs&quot;&gt;Orbigraphs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my main goals currently is to better understand outer automorphisms of
free products of finite groups. I became interested because I like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coxeter_group&quot;&gt;Coxeter groups&lt;/a&gt;,
and I was surprised to hear that we knew so little about their automorphisms.
The natural place to start is the “free” Coxeter group \(W_n\), which is a free product of 
\(n\) copies of \(\mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z\). I’m tempted to say the 
&lt;em&gt;\(n\)th copower of \(\mathbb Z/2\mathbb Z\),&lt;/em&gt; but I guess it’s a little too scary-sounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way I’ve become quite enamored with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orbifold&quot;&gt;orbifolds&lt;/a&gt;. The idea behind
orbifolds is that just as it is useful to study the fundamental group of a manifold both
as a group of homotopy classes of loops and as deck transformations of the universal cover,
so to should there be some object “downstairs” to look at in the case of a group acting
properly discontinuously but not freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An orbigraph, then, is an orbifold quotient of a graph. In other words, the underlying
topological space of an orbigrph is a (typically finite) graph. At a (typically finite)
collection of points called &lt;em&gt;cone points,&lt;/em&gt; there is some nontrivial stabilizer information.
Note that there is the related idea of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_of_groups&quot;&gt;graph of groups&lt;/a&gt;, which is more
general. Since the singular locus of an orbifold is required to be nowhere dense, the term
“orbigraph” succinctly captures the restrictions I require. I also want to think of
orbigraphs as having interesting and nontrivial algebraic topology—in essentially the
same way as in Bass–Serre theory, but I take a slightly less combinatorial bent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper the underlying
space of all orbigraphs in question are finite trees, but I am realizing there is maybe some
(small) usefulness in orbigraphs whose underlying graph is not a tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;train-tracks&quot;&gt;Train Tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main tool for studying automorphisms of free groups is what are called
&lt;em&gt;relative train track maps.&lt;/em&gt; Relative train track maps provide a topological “normal form”
for elements of \(\operatorname{Out}(F_n)\). They were introduced by Bestvina–Handel in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My adaptation to the case of orbigraphs
builds on later developments by Bestvina–Feighn–Handel in 2000 and
Feighn–Handel in 2011. The name “relative train track map” is inspired by the theory
of surface homeomorphisms: there a &lt;em&gt;train track&lt;/em&gt; is a graph embedded into the surface
in a prescribed wy.  The combinatorial properties of certain train tracks associated
to the mapping class of a surface homeomorphism yield a surprisingly rich  amount of
information about the dynamics of the homeomorphism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original idea of Bestvina–Handel’s paper was to attempt to adapt the theory
to study outer automorphisms of free groups. Here, since any homeomorphism of a graph
has a finite power homotopic to the identity, we’re forced to consider homotopy equivalences
of graphs. More explicitly: if \(\varphi \in \operatorname{Out}(F_n)\) is an outer
automorphism of a free group \(F_n\) of rank \(n\), \(G\) is a graph, and \(f\colon G \to G\)
is a homotopy equivalence such that the (outer) action of \(f\) on \(\pi_1(G)\) is equal
to \(\varphi\), then if \(\varphi\) has infinite order, \(f\) cannot be a homeomorphism.
We may as well assume \(f\) sends vertices to vertices.
Stallings tells us that in this situation, there is a vertex \(v\) of \(G\) and a pair of
edges \(e\) and \(e'\) incident to \(v\) such that \(f(e)\) and \(f(e')\) share a common segment.
We say \(f\) &lt;em&gt;folds&lt;/em&gt; these edges, or that they form an &lt;em&gt;illegal turn&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;train track map&lt;/em&gt; has the next best property: We say that \(f\colon G \to G\) is a
&lt;em&gt;train track map&lt;/em&gt; if for each edge \(e\) of \(G\) and each positive integer \(k\),
the \(k\)th iterate, \(f^k(e)\) is an immersed path, i.e. it is never sent over an
illegal turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to try playing with the definition here’s something to try: let
\(G\) be the “rose with four petals.” That is, \(G\) has one vertex and four edges,
each of which forms a loop. Label the edges \(A\) through \(D\) and choose an orientation
for each. Let’s define \(f\) as \(A \mapsto B\), \(B \mapsto C\), \(C \mapsto D\), and
\(D \mapsto AB\), i.e. the path that first follows the edge \(A\) and then \(B\).
There are a few things to check: 1) Find a homotopy inverse for \(f\). 2) Which
turns (pairs of oriented edges originating at a common vertex) are illegal? 3) Is
\(f\) a train track map?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; above is sort of forced on us by the structure of more complicated 
homotopy equivalences: as it turns out,
it may not be the case that we can always avoid illegal turns.
This is especially true in the “bad” case of polynomial growth, about which more below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cat0-free-by-cyclic-groups&quot;&gt;CAT(0) Free-by-Cyclic Groups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gersten in 1994 showed that \(\operatorname{Out}(F_n)\) cannot act
properly and cocompactly on a CAT(0) metric space when \(n \ge 4\).
This is something of a bummer, but also to be expected: Acting by geometrically
on a CAT(0) metric space is a nice situation to be in, and one might think that
\(\operatorname{Out}(F_n)\) should be in some sense too complicated to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out aiming to prove a version of Gersten’s theorem for more general free products,
but instead I found essentially a &lt;em&gt;strong negation&lt;/em&gt; of the situation he described.
Let me describe it in more detail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write \(F_n = \langle x_1,\dotsc,x_n\rangle\), let \(\Phi\) be an automorphism and suppose
that \(\Phi(x_i) = u_ix_iv_i\), where \(u_i,v_i \in \langle x_1,\dotsc,x_{i-1}\rangle\).
Let’s call such  automorphisms &lt;em&gt;upper triangular,&lt;/em&gt; by analogy with groups of matrices.
In the free-by-cyclic group \(F_n\rtimes_\Phi\mathbb{Z} = \langle x_1,\dotsc,x_n,t\rangle\),
this gives us the relation \(tx_it^{-1} = u_ix_iv_i\), which we can rewrite as
\(x_i^{-1}u_i^{-1}tx_i = v_it\), which, if you squint, starts to look like a relation in
an HNN extension with stable letter \(x_i\). In fact, by our assumption on \(u_i\) and \(v_i\),
we actually do get a description of \(F_n\rtimes\mathbb{Z}\) as an iterated HNN extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation can be good and bad. Gersten gave an example of such a description of a free-by-cyclic
group which is a “poison subgroup” for nonpositive curvature. There, \(u_i\) and \(v_i\)
are such that \(u_i^{-1}t\) and \(v_it\) have no business being conjugate in a nice action on a CAT(0) space.
On the other hand, in the situation where they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be conjugate,
Bridson–Haefliger give a construction that allows you to bootstrap a
geometric action on a CAT(0) space up the HNN extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I realized was that in the class of automorphisms I was studying,
if it were the case that the automorphism was already upper-triangular
with respect to the basis \(x_1,\dotsc,x_n\) we were handed, then
\(u_i^{-1}t\) and \(v_it\) were &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; conjugate, so Bridson–Haefliger says we win.
So, my goal in constructing relative train track maps was to find a basis
that has this nice property for a (power of) an arbitrary polynomially-growing
outer automorphism. In the paper, the application is in Section 7, while the
heavy lifting is to find a way to adapt the relative train track technology appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since relative train track maps with nice properties have become a foundational
tool in the study of \(\operatorname{Out}(F_n)\), my hope is that this construction
will help in the study of outer automorphism groups of free products.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I posted my first paper, Train Tracks, Orbigraphs and CAT(0) Free-by-cyclic Groups to the ArXiv! Here is a description of the paper and the idea behind the main application.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Digression</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/13/A-Digression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Digression" /><published>2019-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/13/A-Digression</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/13/A-Digression.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what this post set out to be. It ended up a digression
on set theory vs. category theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern mathematics, there are two notions that might be truly called 
foundational to all the work we do. These are &lt;em&gt;set theory&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;category theory.&lt;/em&gt;
Both theories are living, evolving things with their specialists, constructions
and interesting problems, just like any other field of math, 
but the core ideas are familiar and useful to nearly every mathematician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;set,&lt;/em&gt; naively, is just a way to collect a bunch of objects (called &lt;em&gt;elements&lt;/em&gt;)
together. Since a set only cares about membership or lack thereof, duplicate
elements are ignored. When we’re explicit about them, a set is typically
denoted as a list of elements (thought of as unordered), surrounded by curly braces.
So as sets, \(\{1,2,3,3,5\} = \{1,2,3\}\). A set comprises its elements, nothing more,
nothing less. Thus, maps or functions \(f\) between sets \(X\) and \(Y\) are just
assignments: to each element \(x\) in \(X\), we assign a (unique) element \(f(x)\)
of \(Y\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things, mathematical objects, whatever you can pin down in language,
may be elements (or not) of sets. Sets may even be elements of other sets, although
here is a source of worry. Bertrand Russell observed in 1901 that allowing this
kind of willy-nilly calling things sets yields the mathematical equivalent of the
following silly story: In a small village there is one barber. He shaves the
beards of only those men who does not shave themselves. Who shaves the barber?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question, of course, has no good answer. If the barber shaves himself, then
he cannot, but then he must. The mathematical response to Russell’s realization
was to retrench a bit, but it also paved the way for set theory to become an 
interesting field of research in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set theory, thanks to work of Kurt Goedel and many others, has raised thorny,
even unsolvable, problems that mathematicians working in other fields would often
prefer to gloss over. One example is the following: If you have in front of you
a finite collection of sets, maybe think of them as baskets in the produce section,
you can obviously choose an element from each basket. This process is sometimes
called a &lt;em&gt;choice function.&lt;/em&gt; If you imagine an infinitely long aisle at the grocery
store with baskets evenly spaced along it, you might agree that you can still
choose one element from each basket. Even though you won’t live to see it
through, it’s easy to describe a way to decide how to choose the next element;
each basket is eventually reached by you, even though you will never reach 
every basket. This kind of infinity is &lt;em&gt;countably infinite,&lt;/em&gt; like the numbers
we use for counting. But there are more kinds of infinity, and in those cases
it’s maybe not immediately clear that we should still be able to take an object from
each basket. The hypothesis that we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; is called the &lt;em&gt;Axiom of Choice,&lt;/em&gt; and it
turns out to be “independent” of the rest of the rules of set theory we commonly employ.
That is, the rest of set theory &lt;em&gt;can remain true&lt;/em&gt; whatever position we wish to take on
the axiom of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Category theory, (already touched on implicitly in &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs.html&quot;&gt;The Category of Graphs&lt;/a&gt;) has
a somewhat similar history, although it arose later. Introduced by Samuel Eilenberg
and Saunders Mac Lane in their study of algebraic topology, it has since become
a central perspective in many areas of mathematics and also grown into a field
of interest in its own right. A category is a collection of objects and arrows.
Note that I did not say a &lt;em&gt;set.&lt;/em&gt; This distinction is important theoretically
but in practice categorical and set-theoretic reasoning are typically 
sufficiently different that this can be ignored. In category theory,
the sets themselves comprise a category, typically called &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; with
objects sets and arrows functions between sets. This metaphor motivates
the definition: arrows have a &lt;em&gt;domain&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;codomain,&lt;/em&gt; just as functions
between sets do. Arrows, like functions, may be &lt;em&gt;composed&lt;/em&gt; (i.e.
“first add four, and then multiply by sixteen”), and the composition is
associative, but need not be commutative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This general picture allows one to talk about several different, yet related,
situations together at once. Many common constructions in mathematics, including
“sum” and “product” may be phrased as a certain kind of “universal” construction
in the language of category theory. One such construction, the &lt;em&gt;free object,&lt;/em&gt;
is particularly interesting within group theory. Originally I had meant to talk
about it in this post, but perhaps the next one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m not sure what this post set out to be. It ended up a digression on set theory vs. category theory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Category Of Graphs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Category Of Graphs" /><published>2019-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/29/The-Category-of-Graphs.html">&lt;p&gt;You know the sensation where a familiar word becomes suddenly
completely &lt;em&gt;strange&lt;/em&gt; for no apparent reason? Like suddenly the scales
fall away from your eyes and you see how utterly weird it is that a
concept has a particular name? I’ve been having that feeling with the
word &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt; as I use it in math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a kid, you learn how to &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt; simple functions in the sense of 
being able to sketch them on a sheet of, say, &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt; paper. Millions
of adults probably faintly remember the shape of \(y = x^2\) but aren’t
quite sure why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mathematicians and computer scientists, though, for some reason &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt;
means something similar, but different: to them a graph is an object with
&lt;em&gt;vertices&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt;. Indeed, to Serre, that’s literally all a graph is:
a quadruple \((V,E,\bar{},\iota)\). Two sets, \(V\) and \(E\), represent the
vertices and (oriented) edges of the graph, and \(\bar{}\colon E \to E\) and
\(\iota\colon E \to V\) are functions; \(\bar{e}\) is the edge \(e\) with its
orientation reversed, (so \(\bar{\bar{e}} = e\) for any edge \(e\), but
\(\bar e \neq e\)), and
\(\iota(e)\) represents the initial vertex of the edge \(e\). This lets us
define a function \(\tau\colon E \to V\) picking out the &lt;em&gt;terminal&lt;/em&gt; vertex
of an edge by setting \(\tau(e) = \iota(\bar{e})\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topologist would prefer to say that a graph is a 1-dimensional CW complex.
So rather than an abstract set of vertices, we have a set of points, \(V\),
the \(0\)-cells of our CW complex. And rather than an abstract set of oriented
edges, we have a collection of \(1\)-cells (intervals of the real line) 
whose endpoints are attached to \(0\)-cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two descriptions really are in agreement for most purposes. Maybe one would
prefer the more combinatorial description as a way of “rigidifying” some of the
inherent floppiness of topological spaces. At the same time, using topological methods
allows one access to a whole host of techniques that a too-rigid approach might bury
under a sea of formalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, neither definition really squares with the idea of the graph of
\(y = x^2\), hence why I’ve been feeling weird about the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the &lt;em&gt;category of graphs&lt;/em&gt;, introduced by John Stallings in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.math.ou.edu/~nbrady/teaching/s11-5863/stallings.pdf&quot;&gt;Topology of Finite Graphs&lt;/a&gt;,
building on work of Serre in &lt;a href=&quot;https://d-nb.info/965816907/04&quot;&gt;Trees&lt;/a&gt;, more about which
almost certainly soon, has (as all categories do)
collections of objects and arrows between them.
Here the objects are graphs and arrows are &lt;em&gt;morphisms of graphs.&lt;/em&gt; 
A morphism \(f\colon G \to H\) between
graphs \(G\) and \(H\) is a pair of functions \(f_V\colon V(G) \to V(H)\) 
and \(f_E\colon E(G) \to E(H)\), such that the following diagrams commute:
\(\require{AMScd}\)&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
E(G) @&amp;gt;f_E&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E(H) \\
@V{\iota}VV @V{\iota}VV \\
V(G) @&amp;gt;f_V&amp;gt;&amp;gt; V(H)
\end{CD}\qquad
\begin{CD}
E(G) @&amp;gt;f_E&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E(H) \\
@V\bar{}VV @V\bar{}VV \\
E(G) @&amp;gt;f_E&amp;gt;&amp;gt; E(H)
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;In English what this is saying is that \(f\) preserves the graph structure:
it sends edges to edges, vertices to vertices, \(e\) and \(\bar e\) are sent
to \(f(e)\) and \(\overline{f(e)}\), and the initial vertex of \(e\) is
sent to the initial vertex of \(f(e)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stallings emphasizes the rigidity of morphisms in this construction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By graph and map of graphs, I mean something purely combinatorial or
algebraic. Pictures can be drawn, but one has to understand that maps are
rigid and not just continuous, maps do not collapse edges or wrap edges
around several edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s true; it’s a little challenging to describe precisely which
topological maps between graphs are even homotopic to morphisms without
giving the game (Stallings’ paper) away too quickly!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You know the sensation where a familiar word becomes suddenly completely strange for no apparent reason? Like suddenly the scales fall away from your eyes and you see how utterly weird it is that a concept has a particular name? I’ve been having that feeling with the word graph as I use it in math.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/22/Hello-World.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" /><published>2019-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/22/Hello-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/22/Hello-World.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week,
Marc Weidenbaum of &lt;a href=&quot;https://disquiet.com&quot;&gt;disquiet.com&lt;/a&gt; wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://disquiet.com/2019/06/16/word-blog-20th-anniversary-1999/&quot;&gt;paean
to the blog&lt;/a&gt; that I found really inspiring. “Self-publishing,”
he writes, “is the heart of the healthy internet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So hello. Having been given the push I needed, I decided to
move my academic website to its own URL and use it as an excuse 
to start blogging. Since much of the rest of this website is
given over to my career as a mathematician, it’s reasonable to
expect that I will talk about math here, and I expect to get
technical with it when I want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math is not my only passion. I expect to also talk about
many things related to music. This blog is tentatively titled
Alanza, my middle name, but also my “artist moniker” when 
playing solo. I am a moderator on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co&quot;&gt;lines forum&lt;/a&gt;,
also under the name Alanza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This site is built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and hosted on
GitHub Pages. On lines I asked several questions about how to get
up and running with a website and got &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co/t/blogging-platforms/23333?u=alanza&quot;&gt;a wealth of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;
in response. Although, being a millenial, it’s maybe not surprising
that I’d messed around with HTML as a kid, this site is my first time
using CSS. I read what I could on &lt;a href=&quot;https://every-layout.dev&quot;&gt;Every Layout&lt;/a&gt;
to get a feel for what the concerns were, and borrowed their “Sidebar”
primitive. I also appreciated the from-square-one approach of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://internetingishard.com&quot;&gt;Internetting Is Hard&lt;/a&gt; when Every Layout
went over my head. These resources helped get me up to “okay, I can
Google that” speed.
I also should shout out &lt;a href=&quot;https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2018/08/05/mathjax-in-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Arthur O’Dwyer&lt;/a&gt; for a helpful
blog post about enabling MathJax in Jekyll—which turns out to be 
surprisingly simple!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I taught myself a lot of the basics of typesetting,
so it was eye-opening to see how very different the concerns are
when designing for the web. Although the design here is certainly
minimal, it was also surprisingly relatively painless!
One of my goals for this year has been to improve my Vim skills
and incorporate it more into my work. I was very pleased how well
using Jekyll vs. say, WordPress, furthers this goal!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Earlier this week, Marc Weidenbaum of disquiet.com wrote a paean to the blog that I found really inspiring. “Self-publishing,” he writes, “is the heart of the healthy internet.”</summary></entry></feed>