<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-21T21:37:24-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ryleelyman.github.io</title><subtitle>Website / Blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Free Actions On Real Trees</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/21/Free-actions-on-real-trees.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Actions On Real Trees" /><published>2021-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/21/Free-actions-on-real-trees</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/21/Free-actions-on-real-trees.html">&lt;p&gt;A famous theorem of Rips says that a finitely generated group
with a free action on a &lt;em&gt;real tree&lt;/em&gt; is a free product of free abelian and surface groups.
The purpose of this blog post is to introduce real trees and illustrate this theorem by constructing
free actions of such groups on real trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us begin by defining real trees.
An &lt;em&gt;arc&lt;/em&gt; in a space \(X\) is an embedding \(\gamma\colon [a,b] \to X\)
of a closed interval of \(\mathbb{R}\) in \(X\).
If \((X,d)\) is a metric space,
an arc in \(X\) is a &lt;em&gt;geodesic&lt;/em&gt; if the embedding is an isometric embedding—that is,
for all \(s\) and \(t\) in \([a,b]\), we have&lt;/p&gt;

\[d(\gamma(s),\gamma(t)) = |t - s|.\]

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;real tree&lt;/em&gt; or an \(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;em&gt;-tree&lt;/em&gt; is a metric space \((T,d)\)
in which every two points are joined by a unique arc,
and this arc is the image of a geodesic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples-of-real-trees&quot;&gt;Examples of real trees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see a couple of examples of real trees.
As a first example,
\(\mathbb{R}\) is a real tree.
If \(X\) is a simply connected simplicial complex of dimension \(1\),
that is, a &lt;em&gt;simplicial tree,&lt;/em&gt;
we can define a metric on \(X\)
by declaring each edge of \(X\) to be isometric to an interval of \(\mathbb{R}\) of length \(1\),
and then giving \(X\) the metric where the distance between two points is the length of a shortest path between them.
In this metric, \(X\) becomes a real tree.
The metric topology is in general strictly coarser than the simplicial topology.
This means the “identity” map from the simplicial complex \(X\) to the metric space \(X\) is continuous,
but its inverse need not be continuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;free-abelian-groups-act-freely-on-real-trees&quot;&gt;Free abelian groups act freely on real trees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not hard to construct free actions of finitely generated free abelian groups on real trees,
in fact the word “tree” is somewhat obfuscating:
the real tree in question is the real line \(\mathbb{R}\).
Let \(a_1,\dotsc,a_n\) be a basis for \(\mathbb{Z}^n\).
Have each \(a_i\) act by translation on \(\mathbb{R}\) by some distance \(t_i\).
If the \(t_i\) are not rationally related, then the resulting action of \(\mathbb{Z}^n\) is free.
It also has &lt;em&gt;dense orbits,&lt;/em&gt; a property of some other actions of groups on real trees
that I struggled to visualize—I find this simpler example helpful in that regard!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;surface-groups-act-freely-on-real-trees&quot;&gt;Surface groups act freely on real trees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is admittedly more complicated.
Let \(S\) be a surface equipped with a complete Riemannian metric of constant sectional curvature \(-1\).
A &lt;em&gt;measured geodesic lamination&lt;/em&gt; \((\mathscr{L},\mu)\) on \(S\)
is a closed subset \(\mathscr{L} \subset S\) (the &lt;em&gt;lamination&lt;/em&gt;) which decomposes as a disjoint union of
complete geodesics (called &lt;em&gt;leaves&lt;/em&gt;)
together with a &lt;em&gt;transverse measure&lt;/em&gt; \(\mu\).
This is an assignment, for each arc \(c\) transverse to \(\mathscr{L}\),
of a Radon measure \(\mu|_c\) with support equal to \(c \cap \mathscr{L}\)
that is invariant under homotopy transverse to \(\mathscr{L}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a bit of a mouthful, sorry!
A simple example of a measured geodesic lamination is just a closed geodesic \(\gamma\) on \(S\),
where the transverse measure simply counts the points of intersections of arcs \(c\) with \(\gamma\).
Notice that even if an arc \(c\) transverse to \(\gamma\) is homotopic to an arc with fewer points of intersection,
this homotopy cannot be performed transverse to \(\gamma\), so the measure is really homotopy invariant.
There are measured geodesic laminations with stranger properties
than those that come from closed geodesics,
but I think it can be helpful when trying to picture things involving geodesic laminations,
to just imagine the closed geodesic case and think of a general measured geodesic lamination
as being a sort of generalization or “limit” of this picture.
Thurston has a cute picture in his notes on the geometry and topology of 3-manifolds, see below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/geodesiclamination.png&quot; alt=&quot;Thurston's picture of a geodesic lamination&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let \((\mathscr{L},\mu)\) be a measured geodesic lamination.
We can lift it to a \(\pi_1(S)\)-invariant measured geodesic lamination \((\tilde{\mathscr{L}},\tilde\mu)\)
on the universal cover \(\tilde S\) of \(S\).
I will describe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/004093839190002L&quot;&gt;Morgan and Shalen’s&lt;/a&gt;
construction of a real tree &lt;em&gt;dual&lt;/em&gt; to \((\tilde{\mathscr{L}},\tilde\mu)\).
Since \((\tilde{\mathscr{L}},\tilde\mu)\) is \(\pi_1(S)\)-invariant,
we will obtain an action of \(\pi_1(S)\) by isometries on the dual real tree.
Let \(C\) be the set of complementary components of \(\tilde S\setminus \tilde{\mathscr{L}}\).
Given components \(c\) and \(c'\),
let \(\gamma\) be a path with one endpoint in \(c\) and the other in \(c'\)
such that \(\gamma\) is transverse to \(\tilde{\mathscr{L}}\) and intersects each leaf of \(\tilde{\mathscr{L}}\)
at most once.
For example, given a point \(x\) in \(c\) and \(y\) in \(c'\),
the path \(\gamma\) could be the unique geodesic from \(x\) to \(y\).
Define&lt;/p&gt;

\[d(c,c') = \int_\gamma d\tilde\mu.\]

&lt;p&gt;Morgan and Shalen show that this defines a well-defined distance function on \(C\),
and that this distance satisfies a \(0\)-hyperbolicity condition,
therefore there is a real tree \(T\) equipped with an isometric embedding \(C \to T\)
such that \(T\) is the smallest subtree containing the image of \(C\).
This tree \(T\) is unique up to unique isometry,
so in particular the action of \(\pi_1(S)\) on \(C\) extends to an action on \(T\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us return to our example of a measured geodesic lamination \((\mathscr{L},\mu)\),
where \(\mathscr{L}\) was a closed geodesic \(\gamma\)
and the transverse measure \(\mu\) counted intersection points.
Thinking of \(\gamma\) as an element of \(\pi_1(S)\),
the lamination \(\tilde{\mathscr{L}}\) has a leaf for each conjugate of \(\gamma\) in \(\pi_1(S)\),
and each leaf separates \(\tilde S\) into two components.
The minimal intersection number for a path joining the complementary components is \(1\),
so adjacent components are at distance one in \(T\).
In fact, if you know a little Bass–Serre theory,
the dual tree turns out to be exactly the Bass–Serre tree for the one-edge splitting of \(\pi_1(S)\)
with edge group \(\langle\gamma\rangle\), where each edge has been assigned length \(1\)!
Notice that the action of \(\pi_1(S)\) on this particular tree is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morgan and Shalen show that the stabilizer of a point \(p\) in \(T\) under the action of \(\pi_1(S)\)
is the stabilizer of the corresponding component of \(\tilde S \setminus \tilde{\mathscr{L}}\) if
\(p\) is in the image of \(C\), and is the stabilizer of a leaf of \(\mathscr{L}\) otherwise.
Their key result (which they prove with a Baire Category Theorem argument!)
is the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem.&lt;/strong&gt; If \(S\) is a closed hyperbolic surface that is not the connect sum of three projective planes,
there is a measured geodesic lamination \((\mathscr{L},\mu)\) on \(S\)
all of whose leaves and complementary components are simply connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows that the action of \(\pi_1(S)\) on the dual tree \(T\) is free.
Morgan and Shalen also prove algebraically that if \(S\) &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the connect sum of three projective planes,
then \(\pi_1(S)\) cannot act freely on a real tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;free-products-of-groups-acting-freely&quot;&gt;Free products of groups acting freely&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the remainder of this post,
we will prove the following theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem.&lt;/strong&gt; If \(A\) and \(B\) are groups acting freely on real trees \(S\) and \(T\),
then there is a real tree \(X\) on which the free product \(A*B\) acts freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(G\) is a finitely generated group,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grushko_theorem&quot;&gt;Grushko’s theorem&lt;/a&gt;
says that the number of factors in any free product decomposition of \(G\) is finite,
so applying the theorem inductively provides examples of free actions
of finitely generated free products of free abelian and surface groups.
(Provided, of course, that none of the surfaces in question are the projective plane,
the Klein bottle, or the connect sum of three projective planes.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proof.&lt;/em&gt; The free product \(G = A*B\) acts on a (simplicial) tree \(Y\)
with two orbits of vertices and one orbit of edges with trivial edge stabilizers.
By the orbit stabilizer theorem, the tree has the following description.
The vertex set is the union of the sets of cosets of \(A\) and \(B\) in \(G\),
and the edge set is the set of elements of \(G\).
The edge labeled \(g\) connects the vertices labeled \(gA\) and \(gB\).
Choose points \(s \in S\) and \(t \in T\).
The real tree \(X\) will be constructed in the following way.
We replace vertices of \(Y\) with copies of \(S\) or \(T\), corresponding to whether
the vertex corresponded to a coset of \(A\) or \(B\), respectively,
gluing the edges of \(Y\) so that one endpoint lies in a copy of \(S\) and the other in a copy of \(T\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explicitly the space \(X\) is the quotient of the disjoint union \(G\times S \sqcup G \times T \sqcup G\times [0,1]\)
by the following relations, where \(g \in G\), \(x \in S\), \(y \in T\), \(a \in A\) and \(b \in B\):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\((ga,x) \sim (g,a.x)\),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\((gb,y) \sim (g,b.y)\),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\((g,0) \sim (g,s)\) and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\((g,1) \sim (g,t)\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One checks that the relations imply that there is a copy of \(S\) for each coset \(gA\) in \(G\),
a copy of \(T\) for each coset \(gB\) in \(G\),
and an edge \([0,1]\) for each element of \(G\).
Since \(Y\) was a tree, \(X\) will be a real tree.
The multiplication in the labels of the disjoint union yields an action of \(G\) on \(X\) by isometries.
There is a natural equivariant map \(X \to Y\) that collapses each copy of \(S\) and each copy of \(T\) to a point.
Each element \(g\) of \(G\) either acts freely on \(Y\) (in which case it must act freely on \(X\)),
or it stabilizes a unique vertex of \(Y\), in which case \(g\) is conjugate to an element of \(A\) or \(B\).
In this latter case, \(g\) preserves a copy of \(S\) or \(T\) 
and one checks that it acts as an element of \(A\) or \(B\).
But since the actions of \(A\) and \(B\) were free, it follows that if \(g\) is nontrivial, then it acts freely.
\(\blacksquare\)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A famous theorem of Rips says that a finitely generated group with a free action on a real tree is a free product of free abelian and surface groups. The purpose of this blog post is to introduce real trees and illustrate this theorem by constructing free actions of such groups on real trees.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pullbacks And Intersections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/17/Pullbacks-and-Intersections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pullbacks And Intersections" /><published>2021-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/17/Pullbacks-and-Intersections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/17/Pullbacks-and-Intersections.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a pullback square is an intersection!
Here’s a short post about something cute that came up in my research this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncngt.org&quot;&gt;NCNGT&lt;/a&gt;, which has been very lovely,
my math this week has been carefully walking through a small side proposition
in a paper I’m working on with &lt;a href=&quot;http://cirget.math.uqam.ca/~tyghaswala/&quot;&gt;Ty Ghaswala&lt;/a&gt;.
The idea is that graphs of groups come with a notion of a covering space due to Bass,
and étale groupoids come with their own notion of covering spaces
(for us, we’re following the definition in Bridson–Haefliger),
and given that you can construct an étale groupoid associated to any graph of groups,
I wanted to reconcile the two notions.
The proof ends up being a story of very careful bookkeeping;
I spent much more of this week than I expected trying to gently pin down what goes where
and why and balance the sudden explosion of notation it seemed to require—not the most fun,
but so it goes. And then right at the very end I had this delightful little puzzle. Let me tell you about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I happened to be staring at the following commutative diagram of groups and homomorphisms,
all of which are injective in the particular case I was concerned with&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}\begin{CD}
  \mathscr{L}_{\hat e} @&amp;gt;f_{\hat e}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \mathscr{G}_e \\
  @V\iota_{\hat e}VV @VV\operatorname{ad}(\delta_{\hat e})\iota_eV \\
  \mathscr{L}_w @&amp;gt;f_w&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \mathscr{G}_v.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;It’s not really important what these groups &lt;em&gt;are,&lt;/em&gt;
but in case you’re curious this is a commutative diagram associated to a morphism of graphs of groups—in
my particular case, a covering map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I wanted to know, is the image of \(\mathscr{L}_e\) under these maps
equal to the intersection \(f_w(\mathscr{G}_w) \cap \operatorname{ad}(\delta_{\hat e})\iota_e(\mathscr{G}_e)\)?
Since the situation is pretty general, I wondered if there was maybe a universal property argument:
like, if in the situation above, the square is always a &lt;em&gt;pullback square,&lt;/em&gt;
then maybe we would be able to show that the two subgroups above were equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I had it kind of backwards:
Given injective homomorphisms \(f\colon H \to G\) and \(g\colon K \to G\), the &lt;em&gt;pullback&lt;/em&gt;
\(H\times_G K\) is (up to unique isomorphism) the intersection \(f(H) \cap g(K)\).
Recall that the pullback
is characterized by the following universal property:
it fits in the following commutative diagram&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
  H\times_G K @&amp;gt;\pi_2&amp;gt;&amp;gt; K \\
  @V\pi_1VV @VVgV \\
  H @&amp;gt;f&amp;gt;&amp;gt; G,
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;and is universal for this property in the sense that given a group \(L\)
fitting into the commutative diagram&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
  L @&amp;gt;p_2&amp;gt;&amp;gt; K \\
  @Vp_1VV @VVgV \\
  H @&amp;gt;f&amp;gt;&amp;gt; G
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;there is a unique homomorphism \(q\colon L \to H\times_GK\) such that
\(\pi_2q = p_2\) and \(\pi_1q = p_1.\)
(If there was justice and not MathJax in this world, I’d draw the full commutative diagram I’m alluding to here.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So! Assuming \(f\) and \(g\) are injective, let’s prove that \(H\times_GK\) is the intersection
\(f(H)\cap g(K)\).
This is not hard: first observe that the intersection admits maps \(\pi_1 \colon f(H)\cap g(K) \to H\)
and \(\pi_2\colon f(H)\cap g(K) \to K\):
\(\pi_1\) takes \(g \in f(H)\cap g(K)\), recognizes we can write it as \(f(\hat g)\)
for a unique \(\hat g\) in \(H\), and sends \(g\) to \(\hat g\).
Injectivity of \(f\) assures that this really defines a well-defined homomorphism,
while general properties of functions assure that \(\pi_1\) is injective.
The compositions \(f\pi_1\) and \(g\pi_2\) are the natural inclusion \(\iota\colon f(H)\cap g(K) \to G\).
The map \(\pi_2\) is defined similarly.
Next observe that any group \(L\) fitting into the commutative diagram above
clearly maps into \(f(H)\cap g(K)\), in other words,
the map \(fp_1 = gp_2\) factor through a map \(q\colon L \to f(H)\cap g(K)\) as \(\iota q\).
From here it’s not hard to argue that in fact \(\pi_1q = p_1\) and \(\pi_2q = p_2\); I’ll leave it to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though in my particular situation I had the universals backwards,
I did find this realization clarifying:
it showed that to prove my result,
I needed to show that \(\mathscr{L}_e\) way up above has the universal property of the pullback,
for which it suffices to argue that given an element in the intersection
\(f_w(\mathscr{L}_w) \cap \operatorname{ad}(\delta_{\hat e})\iota_e(\mathscr{G}_e)\),
we can pull it back (as it were) and show that it really comes from an element of \(\mathscr{L}_e\).
This turned out to be true thanks to an extra property my situation enjoys!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Sometimes a pullback square is an intersection! Here’s a short post about something cute that came up in my research this week.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nielsen Realization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/Nielsen-Realization.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nielsen Realization" /><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/Nielsen-Realization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/Nielsen-Realization.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m giving a talk in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncngt.org/home&quot;&gt;Nearly Carbon Neutral Geometric Topology&lt;/a&gt;
about Nielsen realization for infinite-type surfaces.
The format for the conference is that everyone records and uploads their talks beforehand,
and then the conference format allows for discussion and comments via Discord.
The purpose of this post is to share and talk a little bit about my talk, which is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QwA3bSwkcW0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nielsen realization problem was posed by Nielsen in 1932.
The &lt;em&gt;mapping class group&lt;/em&gt; of a surface \(S\),
call it \(\operatorname{Map}(S)\),
is the group of isotopy classes of homeomorphisms of \(S\).
For a subgroup \(G\) of \(\operatorname{Map}(S)\),
it is not generally possible to realize \(G\)
as a group of honest homeomorphisms of \(S\).
Nielsen’s question was whether, in the special case that \(G\) is finite, such a realization is always possible.
Kerckhoff answered Nielsen’s question in the affirmative in 1983 for finite-type surfaces.
In fact, Kerckhoff showed the stronger result that finite subgroups of \(\operatorname{Map}(S)\)
arise as groups of isometries of hyperbolic metrics on \(S\)
(when \(S\) supports a hyperbolic metric, of course).
The first and main theorem I discuss in my talk,
which is joint work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/santanaafton/home&quot;&gt;Santana Afton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.uchicago.edu/~dannyc/&quot;&gt;Danny Calegari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://lvzhouchen.github.io&quot;&gt;Lvzhou Chen&lt;/a&gt;,
is an extension of Kerckhoff’s result to orientable, infinite-type surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kerckhoff’s proof is very cool;
I talk through the main ideas in my talk,
but briefly he defines a \(G\)-invariant, real-valued function on the &lt;em&gt;Teichmüller space of \(S\),&lt;/em&gt;
which parametrizes (homotopy classes of) hyperbolic metrics on \(S\),
and shows that it attains a unique minimum, which is therefore fixed by \(G\).
This fixed point yields a realization of \(G\) as a group of isometries of the corresponding hyperbolic metric.
Kerckhoff’s proof does not work for infinite-type surfaces
basically because a certain finite sum in the definition of his function in the finite-type case
would need to become an infinite series,
and the obvious definition yields a divergent series.
As I mention in the talk,
I’d be very interested in talking with you
if you have ideas about how to weight this series to produce one that converges.
Instead the proof that we give involves cutting our surface up into finite-type pieces,
and applying Kerckhoff’s result to each of the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became interested in infinite-type surfaces and their mapping class groups
after reading a very cool (and short) &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.10060&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;
of &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/lovingmath/home?authuser=0&quot;&gt;Marissa Kawehi Loving&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://justinlanier.org&quot;&gt;Justin Lanier&lt;/a&gt;
finding interesting subgroups of big mapping class groups that cannot be found in finite-type mapping class groups.
It’s a theorem that \(\operatorname{Map}(S)\) is a subgroup of the symmetric group on a countable set.
I wondered whether the symmetric group on a countable set is ever a subgroup of a big mapping class group.
The second result I discuss in the talk has the corollary that &lt;em&gt;no,&lt;/em&gt;
the symmetric group on a countable set cannot continuously embed in any big mapping class group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after reading a draft of our paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.utah.edu/~bestvina/&quot;&gt;Mladen Bestvina&lt;/a&gt; suggested to me
that we should be able to use our techniques to prove that compact subgroups of mapping class groups are finite
and locally compact subgroups are discrete.
After a few days of thinking, I was able to find a proof!
It includes my new favorite way of proving that a group is finite:
show that it is &lt;em&gt;torsion,&lt;/em&gt; that every element has finite order,
and that it is &lt;em&gt;virtually torsion free,&lt;/em&gt; i.e. that it has a finite-index torsion-free subgroup.
Only the trivial subgroup of such a group is torsion free,
so this shows that the trivial subgroup has finite index in the whole group—so the group is finite.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m giving a talk in Nearly Carbon Neutral Geometric Topology about Nielsen realization for infinite-type surfaces. The format for the conference is that everyone records and uploads their talks beforehand, and then the conference format allows for discussion and comments via Discord. The purpose of this post is to share and talk a little bit about my talk, which is below.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Mathematical Postcard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/09/A-Mathematical-Postcard.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Mathematical Postcard" /><published>2021-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/09/A-Mathematical-Postcard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/09/A-Mathematical-Postcard.html">&lt;p&gt;I submitted a “mathematical postcard” (see below)
to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncngt.org&quot;&gt;Nearly Carbon Neutral Geometric Topology&lt;/a&gt; conference.
The purpose of this post is to share the postcard
and offer a little more context and explanation for it.
I’m also giving a talk in said conference,
but I’ll talk about that in a separate post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the postcard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;/assets/pdfs/postcard.pdf&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me say a little more about the space we’re talking about.
Let&lt;/p&gt;

\[F = A_1*\dotsb*A_n*F_k\]

&lt;p&gt;be a free product of the groups \(A_1,\dotsc,A_n\) with a free group of rank \(k\).
It follows from elementary Bass–Serre theory
that \(F\) acts on a (simplicial) tree \(T\) with trivial edge stabilizers
and vertex stabilizers each conjugate to some \(A_i\).
Let’s assume that the action is &lt;em&gt;minimal,&lt;/em&gt; i.e. that there is no proper invariant subtree.
Say two such trees \(S\) and \(T\) are &lt;em&gt;equivalent&lt;/em&gt; if there is an \(F\)-equivariant homeomorphism from \(S\) to \(T\).
It turns out that there are many inequivalent, minimal actions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0501288&quot;&gt;Guirardel and Levitt&lt;/a&gt; define an Outer Space to parametrize them all
(up to a finer notion of equivalence: isometry).
It is a topological space on which the group of those outer automorphisms of \(F\)
which preserve the conjugacy classes of the \(A_i\) acts.
If the \(A_i\) are &lt;em&gt;freely indecomposable,&lt;/em&gt; for example, if they are finite,
then this is all of \(\operatorname{Out}(F)\).
This Outer Space admits a &lt;em&gt;spine,&lt;/em&gt;
a subspace which is a simplicial complex
and onto which it deformation retracts \(\operatorname{Out}(F)\)-equivariantly.
Vertices of the spine are equivalence classes of minimal actions as above.
Two vertices are connected by an edge when one can be obtained from the other by collapsing an orbit of edges.
When \(n \ge 2\), the dimension of this spine is \(n + 2k - 2\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When each \(A_i\) is finite, the spine is locally finite,
and \(\operatorname{Out}(F)\) acts with finite stabilizers and finite quotient.
This is the bread-and-butter situation for geometric group theory,
so outer automorphism groups of free products of finite and cyclic groups are interesting to study as a class
because one can use the geometry of the spine of Outer Space to investigate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again by Bass–Serre theory, one can think of vertices of the spine
via their quotient graphs of groups \(\mathcal{G}\),
as is happening in the postcard.
These quotient graphs of groups will have first Betti number \(k\)
and \(n\) vertices with nontrivial vertex group each isomorphic to one of the \(A_i\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combinatorial types of the examples in the postcard play a particularly special role
in studying the spine of Outer Space.
I call vertices combinatorially equivalent to the first and last examples &lt;em&gt;thistles&lt;/em&gt;
with \(n\) prickles and \(k\) petals (here \(n = 3\) and \(k = 4\)).
Vertices combinatorially equivalent to the middle examples are &lt;em&gt;bugs&lt;/em&gt;
with a head, \(n-1\) legs and \(k\) wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason thistles and bugs are special is illustrated in the postcard:
&lt;em&gt;collapse Whitehead moves&lt;/em&gt; along with their cousins &lt;em&gt;expand Whitehead moves,&lt;/em&gt;
form a system of paths in the spine of Outer Space that connect any two thistles to each other.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2FBF01236258&quot;&gt;Collins and Zieschang&lt;/a&gt; prove a version of Whitehead’s algorithm for free products
using in particular two families of &lt;em&gt;Whitehead automorphisms&lt;/em&gt; that they call \(S\)-Whitehead automorphisms
and \(J\)-multiple Whitehead automorphisms.
The former correspond to expand Whitehead moves, and the latter to collapse Whitehead moves,
and their result says that any two thistles in the spine of Outer Space may be connected by a path of Whitehead moves
which has a very nice interplay with a &lt;em&gt;norm&lt;/em&gt; one can put on thistles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/expandWhitehead.png&quot; alt=&quot;An expand Whitehead move&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me finish by indicating my interest in these paths:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/004093839400042J&quot;&gt;Vogtmann&lt;/a&gt; proved that the outer automorphism group of a free group of rank \(k\)
is what’s called &lt;em&gt;simply connected at infinity&lt;/em&gt; for \(k \ge 5\).
Briefly, a space \(X\) is simply connected at infinity if it has one &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End_(topology)&quot;&gt;end&lt;/a&gt; 
and for any compact subset \(K\),
there is a compact subset \(L\) with \(L \supset K\) such that
any loop in \(X\setminus L\) is nullhomotopic via a homotopy in \(X\setminus K\).
A group is simply connected at infinity if some (and hence any) simplicial complex
on which it acts with finite stabilizers and finite quotient is simply connected at infinity.
So \(\mathbb{R}\) has two ends, \(\mathbb{R}^2\) has one end but is not simply connected at infinity,
and \(\mathbb{R}^{n}\) is simply connected at infinity for \(n \ge 3\);
therefore \(\mathbb{Z}^n\) is simply connected at infinity for \(n \ge 3\).
Vogtmann’s proof involves a careful understanding of the combinatorics of (expand) Whitehead moves
in the spine of Outer Space (for a free group).
I’m in the early stages of working on generalizing her result to free products of finite and cyclic groups.
The general strategy of the proof will follow hers,
but already I am seeing that the presence of collapse Whitehead moves will require their own analysis to handle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I submitted a “mathematical postcard” (see below) to the Nearly Carbon Neutral Geometric Topology conference. The purpose of this post is to share the postcard and offer a little more context and explanation for it. I’m also giving a talk in said conference, but I’ll talk about that in a separate post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes On Orbifolds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/14/Notes-on-Orbifolds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes On Orbifolds" /><published>2021-03-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/14/Notes-on-Orbifolds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/14/Notes-on-Orbifolds.html">&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to share some &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/orbifoldnotes.pdf&quot;&gt;talk notes&lt;/a&gt; I made on orbifolds
and graphs of groups as étale groupoids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk comes out of joint work in progress with &lt;a href=&quot;http://cirget.math.uqam.ca/~tyghaswala/&quot;&gt;Tyrone Ghaswala&lt;/a&gt;.
It starts with us realizing that some representations of the braid group
into the automorphism group of a free group that each of us knew how to obtain by different methods
were really the same representation.
We thought that there ought to be some way to reconcile these two representations topologically
by working with the mapping class group of certain 2-dimensional orbifolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there things got complicated: we discovered that there is a good amount of contention about what
a map of an orbifold even is.
The consensus, outside of low-dimensional topology, seems to be to work with étale groupoids,
rather than deal with orbifolds in terms of local charts.
This has the advantage of making ineffective orbifolds easier.
To wit, see the complications in the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1606.04439.pdf&quot;&gt;Atlases for Ineffective Orbifolds&lt;/a&gt; by Pronk, Scull and Tommasini.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within low-dimensional topology, it’s usually thought that the mapping class group
of a 2-dimensional orbifold whose underlying space is a finite-type surface 
and whose singular set is a finite collection of points
is the subgroup of the mapping class group of the surface where the singular set is marked
preserving the singular points of a given order.
One goal of our project is to reconcile these two points of view.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The purpose of this post is to share some talk notes I made on orbifolds and graphs of groups as étale groupoids.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Train Track Algorithm For Graphs Of Groups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/The-Train-Track-Algorithm-for-Graphs-of-Groups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Train Track Algorithm For Graphs Of Groups" /><published>2020-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/The-Train-Track-Algorithm-for-Graphs-of-Groups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/The-Train-Track-Algorithm-for-Graphs-of-Groups.html">&lt;p&gt;Train track maps, which also come in “relative” and other flavors,
are particularly nice homotopy equivalences of graphs
used as tools to reason about outer automorphisms of free groups.
I wrote a paper extending train track maps (as well as relative train track maps and “CTs”)
to graphs of groups (with trivial edge groups for CTs).
In this post I want to talk a little about how to think about train track maps
and (“tame” in some sense) homotopy equivalences of graphs of groups more generally.
At the end of the post I talk through using the train track algorithm
to compute an example coming from a pseudo-Anosov 5-braid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background-on-graphs-of-groups&quot;&gt;Background on graphs of groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a little background for anyone reading who isn’t an expert in graphs of groups.
The standard reference is Chapter 1 of Serre’s book &lt;em&gt;Trees,&lt;/em&gt; 
which is terse but very good.
Group actions on trees (i.e. simply connected, 1-dimensional simplicial complexes)
crop up all over the place in the theory of infinite groups.
A &lt;em&gt;graph of groups&lt;/em&gt; is a kind of “orbifold quotient” of a group action on a tree.
Technically one needs to assume that the action satisfies the condition of
“no inversions in edges” which means what it probably sounds like
and can always be accomplished by passing to the barycentric subdivision of the tree.
Under this hypothesis, the quotient space of the action is naturally a graph
(i.e. a 1-dimensional CW complex, which will be connected).
Attached to the vertices and edges of the graph are groups
recording stabilizer information.
The “no inversions in edges” hypothesis ensures that if an edge is stabilized by a group element,
then so are the incident vertices,
so there are injective homomorphisms from edge groups into incident vertex groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to like thinking categorically,
a graph of groups can be succinctly described this way.
A graph \(\Gamma\) describes a small category \(\Gamma\) whose objects are the cells of \(\Gamma\)
and whose nonidentity arrows run from edges to incident vertices.
A graph of groups is a functor from the small category \(\Gamma\)
to the category of groups with arrows monomorphisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental theorem of Bass–Serre theory asserts a perfect correspondence between
groups acting on trees on the one hand and graphs of groups on the other.
The exciting part of the theorem says that given a graph of groups,
there is a group, called the &lt;em&gt;fundamental group of the graph of groups&lt;/em&gt;
and a tree, called the &lt;em&gt;Bass–Serre tree&lt;/em&gt; on which it acts
so that the quotient graph of groups is the given graph of groups.
By the way, the fundamental group is really a group of homotopy classes of loops
in the right sense.
In the language of orbifolds, every graph of groups is “good.”
What’s more, a simple presentation of the fundamental group of the graph of groups
can be written down, and the tree and action explicitly described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;morphisms-and-maps-of-graphs-of-groups&quot;&gt;Morphisms and maps of graphs of groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s call a continuous map of graphs a &lt;em&gt;morphism&lt;/em&gt; if it sends vertices to vertices and edges to edges.
There is a notion, due to Bass, of a &lt;em&gt;morphism&lt;/em&gt; of graphs of groups.
It’s a little complicated, so I’d rather talk around it than give a formal definition here.
Suppose \(G\) and \(G'\) are groups acting on trees \(T\) and \(T'\), respectively,
and suppose that we have a homomorphism \(f_\sharp\colon G \to G'\).
A morphism \(\tilde f\colon T \to T'\) is &lt;em&gt;equivariant&lt;/em&gt; with respect to \(f_\sharp\) 
if for all \(g \in G\) and \(x \in T\), we have&lt;/p&gt;

\[\tilde f(g.x) = f_\sharp(g).\tilde f(x).\]

&lt;p&gt;If \(\mathcal{G}\) and \(\mathcal{G}'\) are the quotient graphs of groups,
Bass’s definition is designed so that in this situation there is a morphism \(f\colon\mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\).
Conversely, given a morphism of graphs of groups \(f\colon \mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\),
there is a map \(f_\sharp\colon G \to G'\) and an equivariant map \(\tilde f\colon T\to T'\).
The correspondence is not quite perfect—in some situations there are multiple morphisms of graphs of groups
yielding the same pair \(f_\sharp\) and \(\tilde f\),
but the difference is understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one happens to be categorically minded, it’s possible to give a succinct definition 
of a morphism of graphs of groups.
Suppose \(\mathcal{G}\) and \(\mathcal{G}'\) are graphs of groups with underlying graphs
\(\Gamma\) and \(\Gamma'\), respectively.
A morphism of graphs \(f\colon \Gamma \to \Gamma'\) yields a functor of the associated small categories.
(Indeed, one could eke out slightly more generality 
by defining morphisms of graphs to be those maps yielding a functor of small categories.)
A morphism of graphs of groups is a morphism of underlying graphs \(f\colon \Gamma \to \Gamma'\)
and a &lt;em&gt;pseudonatural transformation&lt;/em&gt; of functors \(f\colon \mathscr{G} \Rightarrow \mathscr{G}'f\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now suppose we have an automorphism \(f_\sharp\colon G \to G\) and a map
\(\tilde f \colon T \to T\) which is equivariant with respect to \(f_\sharp\) 
but may not be a morphism.
After performing a homotopy, 
we may assume that \(\tilde f\) 
is a linear embedding on each edge, 
expanding it over an edge path.
Now \(\tilde f\) will become a morphism after (equivariantly) subdividing each edge into finitely many edges,
so on the quotient graph of groups we are interested in maps 
which may be represented as a subdivision followed by a morphism.
Such a map \(f\colon \mathcal{G}\to\mathcal{G}\) sends vertices to vertices and edges to paths in the graph of groups.
If additionally the image of each edge is a &lt;em&gt;tight&lt;/em&gt; path, i.e. it cannot be shortened by a homotopy,
we’ll call such a map a &lt;em&gt;topological representative.&lt;/em&gt;
For (many) examples of this kind of map, hang on for one more section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;train-track-maps&quot;&gt;Train track maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Train track maps were introduced by Bestvina and Handel in their 1992 paper
“Train tracks and automorphisms of free groups”
to study outer automorphisms of free groups.
They remain one of the main tools for their study.
A topological representative is a &lt;em&gt;train track map&lt;/em&gt; if for each edge \(e\),
the path \(f^k(e))\) is immersed for all \(k \ge 1\),
i.e. it cannot be shortened by a homotopy.
If one accepts immersions and homotopy in a graph of groups sense,
the same definition works for both topological representatives on graphs and on graphs of groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bestvina and Handel describe an algorithm that takes as input an arbitrary topological representative
and progressively either improves it to a train track map or finds an invariant subgraph.
(It is &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; possible to be both a train track map and have an invariant subgraph, 
but these cases are of less interest.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument is a beautiful application of the Perron–Frobenius theory of nonnegative integer matrices.
A nonnegative integer matrix \(M\) is &lt;em&gt;irreducible&lt;/em&gt; if for each \(i\) and \(j\) there exists \(k\)
such that the \(ij\)th entry of \(M^k\) is positive.
To a topological representative \(f\colon \mathcal{G} \to \mathcal{G}\) we can associate a &lt;em&gt;transition matrix&lt;/em&gt;
with rows and columns for each edge of the underlying graph \(\Gamma\)
and \(ij\)th entry the number of times the image of the \(j\)th edge crosses the \(i\)th edge in either direction.
It turns out that the transition matrix of \(f\) is irreducible exactly when \(f\) has no invariant subgraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each irreducible matrix has a real &lt;em&gt;Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue&lt;/em&gt; \(\lambda\) satisfying \(\lambda \ge 1\).
If \(f\) is not a train track map, Bestvina and Handel argue, then the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue may be decreased
by their algorithm.
But by arguing that the number of edges of the graphs they consider remains bounded,
the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue can only be decreased finitely many times before reaching a minimum,
at which point a train track map is reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-pseudo-anosov-braid-example&quot;&gt;A pseudo-Anosov braid example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the algorithm and hopefully offer some illumination on how to think about maps of graphs of groups,
I’d like to compute a train track map for the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0506295&quot;&gt;pseudo-Anosov 5-braid with the least dilatation,&lt;/a&gt;
\(\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\),
seen as an (outer) automorphism of \(W_5\), the free product of 5 copies of the cyclic group of order 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write&lt;/p&gt;

\[W_5 = \langle a_1,a_2,\dotsc,a_5 \mid a_1^2 = a_2^2 = \dotsb = a_5^2 = 1 \rangle.\]

&lt;p&gt;There is a homomorphism from the braid group \(B_n\) to \(\operatorname{Aut}(W_n)\)
sending the generator \(\sigma_i\) to the automorphism&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{cases}
a_i \mapsto a_ia_{i+1}a_i^{-1} \\
a_{i+1} \mapsto a_i \\
a_j \mapsto a_j &amp;amp; j \neq i, i+1.
\end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;There’s a good reason (involving orbifolds) that the homomorphism sends
pseudo-Anosov braids to (outer) automorphisms representable by irreducible train track maps,
but let us just remark that we expect our eventual train track map to have
Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue equal to the dilatation of \(\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\),
that is, \(\lambda \approx 1.722\), the largest root of \(x^4 - x^3 - x^2 - x + 1\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the homomorphism, the action of our element on the generators of \(W_5\) is given by&lt;/p&gt;

\[\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\begin{cases}
a_1 \mapsto a_1a_2a_3a_2^{-1}a_1^{-1} \\
a_2 \mapsto a_1a_2a_4a_2^{-1}a_1^{-1} \\
a_3 \mapsto a_1a_2a_1^{-1} \\
a_4 \mapsto a_1a_5a_1^{-1} \\
a_5 \mapsto a_1.
\end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;To start, we need a graph of groups with fundamental group \(W_5\).
It is a fact that if all edge groups in a graph of groups are trivial,
and the underlying graph is a tree,
then the fundamental group of the graph of groups is isomorphic to the free product of the vertex groups.
Thus a good candidate is the following graph of groups \(\mathcal{G}_1\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/thistle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A graph of groups with fundamental group $$W_5$$&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one vertex with trivial vertex group, five vertices with vertex group cyclic of order 2,
represented in the image by a number 2,
and five edges, each one connecting a vertex with nontrivial vertex group to the vertex with trivial vertex group.
Let us base the fundamental group at the center vertex with trivial vertex group.
Under our identification of this fundamental group with \(W_5\),
a generator of \(W_5\) is represented by a loop that travels out along an edge,
picks up the nontrivial element of the vertex group, and then travels back.
Thus for example \(a_2\) is represented by the loop \(\bar Ba_2B\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s introduce some notation: 
I’ll write a period for the nontrivial element of any vertex group,
and write a hat above an edge to mean traveling along the edge, 
picking up the nontrivial element of the vertex group and then traveling back.
Thus the group element \(a_1a_2a_3a_2^{-1}a_1^{-1}\) is represented in our graph of groups
by the loop \(\hat A\hat B\hat C\hat B\hat A\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may represent \(\sigma_1\sigma_1\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\) by the map
\(f_1\colon \mathcal{G}_1\to\mathcal{G}_1\) defined as&lt;/p&gt;

\[f_1 \begin{cases}
A \mapsto C\hat B \hat A \\
B \mapsto D\hat B \hat A \\
C \mapsto B \hat A \\
D \mapsto E \hat A \\
E \mapsto A
\end{cases}\]

&lt;p&gt;The transition matrix of \(f_1\) is&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{pmatrix}
2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 1 \\
2 &amp;amp; 2 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\
1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\
0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0
\end{pmatrix},\]

&lt;p&gt;whose Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_1\) is the largest real root of
\(-x^5 + 4x^4 + 2x^3 + 4x + 1\) and satisfies \(\lambda_1 \approx 4.577\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we decide whether \(f_1\) is a train track map?
Since \(f_1\) sends edges to tight edge paths,
the only place where cancellation could occur is where the images of edges are joined together.
For example, in \(f_1^2(A)\), there is cancellation between \(f_1(B)\) and \(f_1(\bar A)\)
because the last edge of \(f_1(B)\), namely \(A\), is equal to the reverse of the first edge of \(f_1(\bar A)\).
Thus we know \(f_1\) is not a train track map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can formalize this as follows: a &lt;em&gt;turn&lt;/em&gt; is a pair of edges sharing a common initial vertex,
e.g. \(\{\bar A,\bar A\}\) or \(\{\bar B,\bar C\}\).
The former turn is &lt;em&gt;degenerate,&lt;/em&gt; while the latter is not.
If the vertex in question has nontrivial vertex group,
rather than just pairs of edges,
we should consider pairs of pairs consisting of an edge together with a vertex group element.
Thus at the initial vertex of the edge \(A\),
the turn \(\{.A,A\}\) is nondegenerate.
A topological representative \(f\colon \mathcal{G} \to \mathcal{G}\) induces a map \(Tf\)
on the set of turns by sending \(\{E,E'\}\) to the
turn determined by the initial edges in the image of \(f(E)\) and \(f(E')\).
A turn is &lt;em&gt;illegal&lt;/em&gt; if it is eventually mapped to a degenerate turn.
In our example, every turn based at the center vertex is illegal because
each such turn is mapped to \(\{\bar A,\bar A\}\).
Thus we can say that \(f_1\) is not a train track map
because, for instance, the image of \(f_1(A)\) contains the illegal turn \(\{\bar B,\bar A\}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the situation, let’s &lt;em&gt;fold&lt;/em&gt; \(\bar A\) and \(\bar B\). 
They each have initial segments mapped to the path \(\hat A\hat B\),
so subdivide at the endpoint of these initial segments and then identify them to create a new edge as pictured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/fold1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Folding the edges $$\bar A$$ and $$\bar B$$&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The correspondence \(A \leadsto A'F\) and \(B \leadsto B'F\) allows us to define
a new map on our new graph of groups \(f_2\colon \mathcal{G}_2\to \mathcal{G}_2\).
The new map admits some tightening, which yields a corresponding reduction in the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue
\(\lambda_2\),
which is now the largest root of the polynomial \(x^6 - 2x^5 - 2x^4 - 4x^2 + 3x + 2\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_2 \approx 2.994\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The second topological representative&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the map \(f_2\) is still not a train track map, 
since every turn based at either of the vertices with trivial vertex stabilizer is eventually mapped to
\(\{\bar F,\bar F\}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The second map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s fold again, this time identifying all of \(E\) with an initial segment of \(\bar F\).
The correspondence \(F \leadsto F'E\) yields a new map \(f_3\colon \mathcal{G}_3 \to \mathcal{G}_3\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The third topological representative&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_3\) is the largest root of
\(x^6 - 2x^5 - 2x^4 - 2x^3 + 5x - 2\) and satisfies \(\lambda_3 \approx 2.875\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The third map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still illegal turns, so let’s fold \(C\) and \(D\) with \(E\) to produce a valence-one vertex
with trivial vertex group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/fold3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The third fold&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folding doesn’t produce any cancellation, so the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue is unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The fourth and fifth maps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The valence-one homotopy does decrease the Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue;
\(\lambda_5\) is the largest root of \(-x^5 + x^4 + x^3 + x^2 + x - 2\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_5 \approx 1.830\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The fifth map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image of \(F'\) contains the illegal turn \(\{\bar A',\bar B'\}\),
which is first mapped to \(\{\bar C',\bar D'\}\) before degenerating.
So we’ll fold \(\bar D'\) and \(\bar C'\), then \(\bar A'\) and \(\bar B'\), 
and then the interior of \(F'\) if need be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The sixth and seventh maps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, the second fold produces nontrivial tightening;
\(\lambda_7\) is the largest root of \(-x^7 + x^6 + x^5 + x^4 + x^3 - 2x^2 - 2\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_7 \approx 1.789\).
We have produced a vertex of valence two with trivial vertex group and would like to get rid of it via a homotopy.
The eigenvector coefficient of the edge \(G\) is larger than the eigenvector coefficient for \(F'\),
so we collapse \(G\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The eighth map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_8\) is the largest root of
\(x^6 - x^5 - 2x^3 - x - 1\) and satisfies \(\lambda_8 \approx 1.783\).
The turn \(\{\bar E',\bar F'\}\) is illegal and in the image of \(F'\), so we fold them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/map9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The ninth map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perron–Frobenius eigenvalue \(\lambda_9\) is the largest root of \(x^6 - x^5 - 2x^3 - x + 1\)
and satisfies \(\lambda_9 \approx 1.722\).
The only turns that we need to worry about in the image of edges of \(f_9\) are \(\{E',\bar F''\}\)
and \(\{\bar B'',F''\}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/traintrack/turns9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The ninth map on turns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, both of these turns are legal, so this is a train track map!
Indeed \(\lambda_9\) is also the largest real root of \(x^4 - x^3 - x^2 - x + 1\),
the polynomial we mentioned before in connection with \(\sigma_1\sigma_2\sigma_3\sigma_4\sigma_1\sigma_2\).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Train track maps, which also come in “relative” and other flavors, are particularly nice homotopy equivalences of graphs used as tools to reason about outer automorphisms of free groups. I wrote a paper extending train track maps (as well as relative train track maps and “CTs”) to graphs of groups (with trivial edge groups for CTs). In this post I want to talk a little about how to think about train track maps and (“tame” in some sense) homotopy equivalences of graphs of groups more generally. At the end of the post I talk through using the train track algorithm to compute an example coming from a pseudo-Anosov 5-braid.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Axiom Of Choice Is False For Manifolds</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/The-Axiom-of-Choice-is-False-for-Manifolds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Axiom Of Choice Is False For Manifolds" /><published>2020-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/The-Axiom-of-Choice-is-False-for-Manifolds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/02/The-Axiom-of-Choice-is-False-for-Manifolds.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a post about one of those things that is really a case of category theory
cheekily playing with unhooking a signifier from what it typically signifies.
Namely, one of the (many) tricky foundational things about working with orbifolds
goes by the name “the axiom of choice is false for the category of smooth manifolds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to misinterpret the statement is to take it literally:
as undergraduate math majors learn, the axiom of choice says that given an infinite collection of sets,
you can always choose exactly one element of each set, even if the collection is infinite.
Therefore the statement “the axiom of choice is false for the category of smooth manifolds”
could reasonably be thought to mean “given a collection of smooth manifolds,
which are in particular sets with additional structure,
it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case that you can always choose a point in each manifold if the collection is sufficiently large.”
Of course, if we accept the axiom of choice 
(I do, since I like the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nielsen–Schreier_theorem#Axiomatic_foundations&quot;&gt;Nielsen–Schreier theorem&lt;/a&gt;
which says that subgroups of free groups are free), 
then this statement is nonsense: it doesn’t matter if the collection of sets is really a collection of manifolds
or a collection of the contents of various grocery stores, we can always choose one element from each.
What, then, does this statement mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, there are two statements equivalent to the axiom of choice that have category-theoretic import.
This post is primarily concerned with the latter, but the former is too cute to pass up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;every-epimorphism-splits&quot;&gt;Every Epimorphism Splits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set theory is kind of in an odd position within mathematics.
I read some complaint that most mathematicians see sets every day
and yet have never seen sets be &lt;em&gt;interesting,&lt;/em&gt; 
and so discount the possibility that set theory could be a worthwhile pursuit.
The standard formulation of set theory as a foundation for mathematics is somewhat unfortunate, too:
if we take the axioms of Zermelo–Frankel set theory too literally, then we notice that everything is a set,
even the elements of sets.
Thus nonsensical questions like “what are the elements of 6” are allowable on a technicality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned this complaint, and everything in this section, from a beautiful 8-page article by Tom Leinster called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1212.6543.pdf&quot;&gt;“Rethinking Set Theory”&lt;/a&gt; from which I’d like to quote most of the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mathematicians manipulate sets with confidence almost every day, rarely making mistakes. 
Few of us, however, could accurately quote what are often referred to as “the” axioms of set theory. 
This suggests that we all carry around with us, perhaps subconsciously, 
a reliable body of operating principles for manipulating sets. 
What if we were to take some of those principles and adopt them as our axioms instead? 
The message of this article is that this can be done, in a simple, practical way (due to Lawvere). 
The resulting axioms are ten thoroughly mundane statements about sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these axioms, the formulation of the axiom of choice is perhaps the most devastatingly simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.&lt;/strong&gt; Every [surjective function of sets] has a right inverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see that this is really equivalent, notice that if \(p\colon S \to T\) is a surjective function of sets,
then we may identify \(S\) with the disjoint union&lt;/p&gt;

\[\coprod_{t \in T} p^{-1}(t).\]

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;right inverse&lt;/em&gt; for the function \(p\) is a function \(i \colon T \to S\)
such that \(p(i(t)) = t\) for all \(t\) in \(T\).
Notice that this means that \(i\colon T \to S\) picks out one element of \(p^{-1}(t)\) as \(t\)
varies over the elements of \(T\),
so the existence of such a function is equivalent to being able to perform choice in the sense that we said above!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This axiom can be reformulated in any category:
the correct generalization of a surjective function is called an &lt;em&gt;epimorphism;&lt;/em&gt;
for categories of “sets with additional structure” (e.g. groups, rings, manifolds) the surjective maps 
are epimorphisms, but the converse is not always true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A right inverse for an arrow \(f\colon c \to d\) makes sense in any category:
it’s an arrow \(r \colon d \to c\) such that \(fr\) is the identity arrow of \(c\).
It’s a general fact that admitting a right inverse implies that the arrow is an epimorphism,
even though we haven’t defined what that is.
In fact, for categories of “sets with additional structure” if \(f\) admits a right inverse,
then it is surjective.
We say \(f\) is a &lt;em&gt;split epimorphism&lt;/em&gt; (the name comes from “split exact sequences” of e.g. groups).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to cheekily reformulate the axiom of choice in any category as the following statement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Axiom of Choice for a Category:&lt;/strong&gt; every epimorphism is split.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This axiom fails for smooth manifolds:
a surjective map from the real line to the unit circle in \(\mathbb R^2\) given by sending \(x\)
to \((\cos x,\sin x)\) for instance, fails to have a right inverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-equivalent-definition-of-equivalence-of-categories&quot;&gt;An Equivalent Definition of Equivalence of Categories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another use of the axiom of choice in category theory is the following theorem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt; A functor \(F\colon C \to D\) between categories \(C\) and \(D\) is an &lt;em&gt;equivalence of categories&lt;/em&gt;
if and only if it is &lt;em&gt;fully faithful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;essentially surjective.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the functor \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;full&lt;/em&gt; if for all objects \(c\) and \(c'\) in \(C\), the function
\(F\colon C(c,c') \to D(Fc,Fc')\) is surjective, and &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; if it is injective.
So \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;fully faithful&lt;/em&gt; if it induces a bijection from the set of arrows betwwen any two objects in \(C\)
to their images in \(D\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functor \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;essentially surjective&lt;/em&gt; if every object \(d \in D\) is isomorphic to \(Fc\) for some
\(c \in C\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally an &lt;em&gt;equivalence of categories&lt;/em&gt; is a functor \(F\colon C \to D\) such that there exists an “inverse”
functor \(G \colon D \to C\) and natural isomorphisms between the two double compositions and the
identity functors of \(C\) and \(D\), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof that an equivalence of categories has the above properties is fairly simple: in an alternate universe,
this blog post would give it, and show that the converse requires the axiom of choice.
Let me just content myself with pointing out that the use of the axiom of choice is to pick
a \(c\) such that \(Fc\) is isomorphic to \(d\) for all \(d \in D\).
In fact, it turns out that the theorem is &lt;em&gt;equivalent&lt;/em&gt; to the axiom of choice,
if you make the appropriate definitions of the categories involved.
(e.g. \(D\) should be an index set, and \(C\) a clever category based on a collection
of sets indexed by \(D\).)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can define (small) categories &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; to a category and 
do category theory in this way. Thus one way to phrase the axiom of choice for a category is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Axiom of Choice for a Category:&lt;/strong&gt; A functor between categories internal to \(C\)
is an equivalence if and only if it is fully faithful and essentially surjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the category of smooth manifolds &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; fails this axiom,
essentially because it fails the previous one!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a post about one of those things that is really a case of category theory cheekily playing with unhooking a signifier from what it typically signifies. Namely, one of the (many) tricky foundational things about working with orbifolds goes by the name “the axiom of choice is false for the category of smooth manifolds.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Sheafy Adjunction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/26/A-Sheafy-Adjunction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Sheafy Adjunction" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/26/A-Sheafy-Adjunction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/26/A-Sheafy-Adjunction.html">&lt;p&gt;Given a topological space \(X\) and a continuous map \(\pi\colon X \to Y\),
there is an adjunction between the categories of sheaves on \(X\) and sheaves on \(Y\).
The adjunction is somewhat mysterious to me as I begin to write this,
so the hope is that by writing about it, I’ll begin to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functors in question are the &lt;em&gt;pushforward&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;inverse image&lt;/em&gt; functors,
which arise naturally in algebraic geometry (so I am led to believe).
What makes the adjunction difficult to understand is that the definitions
of the functors in question don’t seem to play nicely with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof (with a little setting the stage) appears below.
The method of proof, like most category-theoretic proofs,
is a story of careful bookkeeping with functors and natural transformations,
along with simple calculations to check.
The idea essentially seems to be that the 
unit \(\eta_\mathscr{F} \colon \mathscr{F} \to \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}\)
“shreds a section \(f\) into pieces,” while the counit
\(\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}} \colon \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}\)
recognizes that these “shredded up” sections assemble into sections of \(\mathscr{G}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adjunctions&quot;&gt;Adjunctions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, given categories \(C\) and \(D\), a pair of functors
\(F \colon C \to D\) and \(G \colon D \to C\) form an &lt;em&gt;adjoint pair&lt;/em&gt;
when there exists an isomorphism&lt;/p&gt;

\[D(Fc,d) \cong C(c,Gd)\]

&lt;p&gt;which is natural in \(c\) and \(d\).
We say \(F\) is &lt;em&gt;left adjoint&lt;/em&gt; to \(G\),
or equivalently that \(G\) is &lt;em&gt;right adjoint&lt;/em&gt; to \(F\).
In particular, setting \(d = Fc\), we have&lt;/p&gt;

\[D(Fc,Fc) \cong C(c,GFc).\]

&lt;p&gt;which gives us a natural transformation \(\eta \colon 1_C \Longrightarrow GF\).
Similarly, we have \(\epsilon\colon FG \Longrightarrow 1_D\).
The natural transformation \(\eta\) is called the &lt;em&gt;unit&lt;/em&gt; of the adjunction,
and \(\epsilon\) is the &lt;em&gt;counit.&lt;/em&gt;
In fact, the existence of these natural transformations
could be taken to be the &lt;em&gt;definition&lt;/em&gt; of an adjunction,
provided the natural transformations satisfy the identities&lt;/p&gt;

\[\epsilon F \circ F\eta = 1_F \quad\text{and}\quad G\epsilon \circ \eta G = 1_G,\]

&lt;p&gt;which says that for all \(c \in C\) and \(d \in D\), the compositions&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}
\begin{CD}
Fc @&amp;gt;{F\eta_c}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; FGFc @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{Fc}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Fc
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
Gd @&amp;gt;{\eta_{Gd}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; GFGd @&amp;gt;{G\epsilon_d}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Gd
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;are the identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal in this blog post is to show that the functors I am interested in
satisfy this latter definition of an adjunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sheaves&quot;&gt;Sheaves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a pair of spaces \(X\) and \(Y\), and a continuous map \(\pi \colon X \to Y\),
we have functors \(\pi_\ast \colon \operatorname{Sh}_X \to \operatorname{Sh}_Y\)
and \(\pi^{-1}\colon \operatorname {Sh}_Y \to \operatorname{Sh}_X\) from the category
of sheaves on \(X\) to the category of sheaves on \(Y\) and &lt;em&gt;vice versa.&lt;/em&gt;
The former is simple to describe: if \(\mathscr{G}\) is a sheaf on \(X\),
the &lt;em&gt;pushforward sheaf&lt;/em&gt; \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\) on \(Y\) is the assignment&lt;/p&gt;

\[U \mapsto \mathscr{F}(\pi^{-1}(U))\]

&lt;p&gt;for all open subsets \(U\) of \(Y\).
If \(\psi \colon \mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\) is a morphism of sheaves on \(X\),
the morphism \(\pi_\ast\psi\) is defined by the rule&lt;/p&gt;

\[(\pi_\ast\psi)(U) = \psi(\pi^{-1}(U)).\]

&lt;p&gt;The latter is slightly more complicated.
Recall that if \(\mathscr{F}\) is a sheaf on \(Y\),
there is a space \(F\) equipped with a local homeomorphism \(\rho \colon F \to Y\).
The sheaf \(\mathscr{F}\) is the sheaf of local sections of \(\rho\);
\(F\) is called the &lt;em&gt;espace étale&lt;/em&gt; for the sheaf \(\mathscr{F}\).
The set of points of \(F\) above \(y \in Y\) is the &lt;em&gt;stalk&lt;/em&gt; \(\mathscr{F}_y\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, a section \(s\colon U \to F\) of the projection \(\rho \colon F \to X\)
is an element \((s_y)_{y \in U}\) of \(\prod_{y \in U} \mathscr{F}_y\).
In our case, continuity of \(s\) is the following condition&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}\label{star}\tag{$\ast$}
\text{for all } y \in U, \text{ there exists an open neighborhood }
U_y \text{ of } y\\  \text{ and } f\in\mathscr{F}(U_y) \text{ such that }
f_x = s_x \text{ for all } x \in U_y.
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Given that \(F\) and \(X\) admit maps to \(Y\), we can form their pullback,&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi^{-1}F @&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; F \\
@VVV @VV{\rho}V \\
X @&amp;gt;{\pi}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Y
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;which as a set is  \(\{ (x,f_y) \in X \times F : \pi(x) = y\}\).
The topology on \(\pi^{-1}F\) is induced from the product topology on \(X \times F\).
The &lt;em&gt;inverse image sheaf&lt;/em&gt; \(\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}\) is the sheaf of sections of \(\pi^{-1}F \to X\).
The universal property of the pullback ensures that this really defines a functor
from the category of sheaves on \(Y\) to the category of sheaves on \(X\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Condition \(\eqref{star}\) for continuity of a section \(s\colon V \to \pi^{-1}F\)—that is,
a tuple \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) in \(\prod_{x \in V}\mathscr{F}_{\pi(x)}\)—says
that for all \(x \in V\) there exists an open neighborhood \(V_x\) of \(x\)
and an open neighborhood \(U_x\) in \(Y\) such that \(\pi(V_x) \subset U_x\).
Furthermore there exists a section \(f \in \mathscr{F}(U_x)\) 
such that \(f_{\pi(v)} = s_{\pi(v)}\) for all \(v \in V_x\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(\phi\colon \mathscr{F} \to \mathscr{F}'\) is a morphism of sheaves on \(Y\),
the resulting morphism \(\pi^{-1}\phi \colon \pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} \to \pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}'\)
is defined by&lt;/p&gt;

\[(\pi^{-1}\phi)(V)\left[(s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\right] = \left(\phi_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in V}.\]

&lt;p&gt;One needs to demonstrate that the right-hand side satisfies condition \(\eqref{star}\);
the check is simple, so I’ll leave it to the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim is that \(\pi^{-1}\) is left adjoint to \(\pi_\ast\).
Therefore we should expect natural transformations
\(\eta \colon 1_{\operatorname{Sh}_Y} \Longrightarrow \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\)
and \(\epsilon \colon \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast \Longrightarrow 1_{\operatorname{Sh}_X}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-unit-of-the-adjunction&quot;&gt;The Unit of the Adjunction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let \(\mathscr{F}\) be a sheaf on \(Y\),
and let \(U\) be an open set in \(Y\).
Since \(\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U) = \pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(\pi^{-1}(U))\),
we can think of \(s \in \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U)\) as
a section \(s \colon \pi^{-1}(U) \to \pi^{-1}F\),
i.e. a tuple \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)}\)
satisfying the compatibility condition above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in particular if \(U \subset Y\) is open
and \(f \in \mathscr{F}(U)\), the continuity condition \(\eqref{star}\)
for a section \(\pi^{-1}(U)\to \pi^{-1}F\) is satisfied by the section
\((f_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)}\),
and thus defines an element of \(\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us thus define a map \(\eta_{\mathscr{F}}(U)\colon \mathscr{F}(U) \to \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U)\) 
as&lt;/p&gt;

\[\eta_{\mathscr{F}}(U)(f) = (f_{\pi(x)})_{x\in\pi^{-1}(U)}.\]

&lt;p&gt;(Let’s parse the notation: a natural transformation \(\eta\) yields
a map of sheaves \(\eta_{\mathscr{F}}\) for each sheaf \(\mathscr{F}\).
This is the definition of that map on the open subset \(U \subset Y\).)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prove the claim that \(\eta\) is a natural transformation,
we need to show that given a map \(\phi \colon \mathscr{F} \to \mathscr{F}'\)
of sheaves on \(Y\), the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\mathscr{F} @&amp;gt;{\eta_{\mathscr{F}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} \\
@V{\phi}VV @VV{\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\phi}V \\
\mathscr{F}' @&amp;gt;{\eta_{\mathscr{F}'}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}'.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Given \(f \in \mathscr{F}(U)\), commutativity of the square is the claim that
the following equality holds&lt;/p&gt;

\[\left((\phi(U)(f))_{\pi(x)}\right)_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)} 
= \left(\phi_{\pi(x)}(f_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)}.\]

&lt;p&gt;This is in fact true, since taking the stalk at \(x\) is functorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-counit-of-the-adjunction&quot;&gt;The Counit of the Adjunction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now suppose that \(\mathscr{G}\) is a sheaf on \(X\).
Let \(\pi_\ast G\) denote the &lt;em&gt;espace étale&lt;/em&gt; over \(Y\) for the sheaf \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A section \(s \colon V \to \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast G\)
is a tuple \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) taking values in \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}_{\pi(x)}\)
satisfying the continuity condition \(\eqref{star}\),
which in our particular case asserts the existence,
for each \(x \in V\), of an open neighborhood \(V_x\) of \(x\) and an open neighborhood
\(U_x\) in \(Y\) satisfying \(\pi(V_x) \subset U_x\).
Furthermore there exists \(g \in \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U_x) = \mathscr{G}(\pi^{-1}(U_x))\)
such that the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\) in \(\mathscr{G}_x\) under the natural map
\(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}_{\pi(x)} \to \mathscr{G}_x\) is equal to \(g_x\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the sets \(\pi^{-1}(U_x)\) cover \(V\) by assumption,
sheafiness of \(\mathscr{G}\) implies the existence of a unique \(g \in \mathscr{G}(V)\)
such that \(g_x\) is equal to the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\)
under the natural map \(\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}_{\pi(x)} \to \mathscr{G}_x\)
for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; \(x \in V\).
Let us thus define a map \(\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}}(V) \colon \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(V) \to \mathscr{G}(V)\)
sending \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x\in V}\) to \(g\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We claim that \(\epsilon\) defines a natural transformation from \(\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\) to \(\mathscr{G}\).
To prove the claim, we need to show that given a map \(\psi\colon \mathscr{G} \to \mathscr{G}'\)
of sheaves on \(X\), the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G} @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \mathscr{G} \\
@V{\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\psi}VV @VV{\psi}V \\
\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast \mathscr{G}' @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}'}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \mathscr{G}'.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;Given \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V} \in \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(V)\),
the upper right path of the square sends us first to some \(g \in \mathscr{G}(V)\)
such that \(g_x\) is the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\) in \(\mathscr{G}_x\) for all \(x \in V\),
and then sends \(g\) to \(\psi(V)(g) \in \mathscr{G}'(V)\).
On the other hand, the lower left path of the square sends
\((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) first to \(\left((\pi_\ast\psi)_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in V}\)
in \(\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}'(V)\), and then to
some \(g' \in \mathscr{G}'(V)\) such that \(g'_x\) is the image of
\((\pi_\ast\psi)_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\) in \(\mathscr{G}'_x\) for all \(x \in V\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(U \subset Y\) is an open set containing \(\pi(x)\) such that
\(s \in \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U) = \mathscr{G}(\pi^{-1}(U))\) 
represents \(s_{\pi(x)}\) for \(\pi(x) \in U\),
we have \((\pi_\ast\psi)_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)}) = \psi(\pi^{-1}(U))(s)_{\pi(x)}\).
Furthermore we know that \(g \in \mathscr{G}(V)\) 
is such that the image of \(s_{\pi(x)}\) in \(\mathscr{G}_x\)
is \(g_x\) for all \(x \in V\).
Therefore we have that
the image of \(\psi(\pi^{-1}(U))(s)_{\pi(x)}\)
in \(\mathscr{G}'_x\) is equal to \(\psi(V)(g)_x\),
as desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-inverse-imagepushforward-adjunction&quot;&gt;The inverse image–pushforward adjunction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, we just need to show that two double compositions
of natural transformations are the identity.
The first, translated into our particular case,
says that if \(\mathscr{F}\) is a sheaf on \(Y\),
we have that&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} @&amp;gt;{\pi^{-1}\eta_{\mathscr{F}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F} @&amp;gt;{\epsilon_{\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;is equal to the identity.
The difficulty here seems to be largely notational.
Let \(V \subset X\) be an open set.
Suppose \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) is a section in \(\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(V)\).
We have&lt;/p&gt;

\[(\pi^{-1}\eta_{\mathscr{F}})(V)\left[(s_{\pi(x)})_{x\in V}\right]
= \left((\eta_{\mathscr{F}})_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\right)_{x \in V}
\in \pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(V).\]

&lt;p&gt;First observe that the continuity condition \(\eqref{star}\) tells us that
there is, for each \(x \in V\), an open neighborhood \(V_x\) of \(x\) and
an open set \(U_x \subset Y\) containing \(\pi(V_x)\).
On this open set we have \(s \in \mathscr{F}(U_x)\) such that
\(\left((\eta_{\mathscr{F}})(U_x)(s)\right)_{\pi(x)} = (\eta_{\mathscr{F}})_{\pi(x)}(s_{\pi(x)})\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw above that \((\eta_{\mathscr{F}})(U_x)(s)\) is the section
\((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U_x)} \in \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(U_x) = 
\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(\pi^{-1}(U))\).
The map \(\epsilon_{\pi^{-1}\mathscr F}\) recognizes that the sections
\((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U_x)}\) satisfy the compatibility conditions
to glue up to form a section \((s_{\pi(x)})_{x \in V}\) in \(\pi^{-1}\mathscr{F}(V)\),
demonstrating that the double composition is indeed the identity. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second double composition we need to show is equal to the identity is defined 
for a sheaf \(\mathscr{G}\) on \(X\) as follows&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
\pi_\ast\mathscr{G} @&amp;gt;{\eta_{\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}
@&amp;gt;{\pi_\ast\epsilon_{\mathscr{G}}}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}.
\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;If \(U \subset Y\) is an open set and \(g \in \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U)\)
is a section,
the first map sends \(g\) to the section
\((g_{\pi(x)})_{x \in \pi^{-1}(U)} \in \pi_\ast\pi^{-1}\pi_\ast\mathscr{G}(U)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second map recognizes that the above section and \(g \in \mathscr{G}(\pi^{-1}(U)) = \pi_\ast\mathscr{G}\)
agree on each stalk, and so sends our section back to \(g\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This completes the proof that inverse image and pushforward form an adjoint pair of functors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Given a topological space \(X\) and a continuous map \(\pi\colon X \to Y\), there is an adjunction between the categories of sheaves on \(X\) and sheaves on \(Y\). The adjunction is somewhat mysterious to me as I begin to write this, so the hope is that by writing about it, I’ll begin to understand.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two Approaches To The Cotangent Space</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/Two-Approaches-to-the-Cotangent-Space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two Approaches To The Cotangent Space" /><published>2020-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/Two-Approaches-to-the-Cotangent-Space</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/Two-Approaches-to-the-Cotangent-Space.html">&lt;p&gt;There is a “sheaf-theoretic” definition of something like a &lt;em&gt;cotangent space at a point&lt;/em&gt;
for a locally-ringed space.
In the case of the sheaf of differentiable functions on a smooth manifold,
the two definitions—sheaf-theoretic and the usual one in differential geometry—agree.
What’s more, modulo the appropriate background technology in both subjects,
the proof is beautiful and simple—I feel like shouting it from the rooftops
at the moment, so this blog post will try and give a little exposition.
I’ll try to move briskly without assuming total familiarity with either side of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-algebraic-cotangent-space&quot;&gt;The Algebraic Cotangent Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let \(X\) be a smooth manifold of dimension \(n\).
The &lt;em&gt;sheaf&lt;/em&gt; of differentiable functions on \(X\) is a
contravariant functor from the category of open subsets of \(X\) to the category of rings
that assigns to an open set \(U\)
the ring \(\mathscr{O}(U)\) of differentiable functions \(f\colon U \to \mathbb{R}\)—addition
and multiplication in \(\mathscr{O}(U)\) are done pointwise in \(\mathbb{R}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sheaf is not so important for us;
what we are interested in today are the &lt;em&gt;stalks.&lt;/em&gt;
The idea is that elements of the &lt;em&gt;stalk,&lt;/em&gt;
called &lt;em&gt;germs,&lt;/em&gt; capture the “infinitesimal behavior”
of smooth functions at a point.
Here is the formal definition.
Given a point \(p \in X\), 
the &lt;em&gt;stalk&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;germs&lt;/em&gt; of smooth functions at \(p\) is the ring&lt;/p&gt;

\[\mathscr{O}_p = \{(f,U) : f \in \mathscr{O}(U),\ p\in U \}/\sim.\]

&lt;p&gt;The equivalence relation \(\sim\) is defined as follows:
we say \((f,U) \sim (g,V)\) if there exists an open neighborhood
\(U' \subset U \cap V\) such that \(f|_{U'} = g|_{U'}\).
The equivalence class of \((f,U)\) is its &lt;em&gt;germ.&lt;/em&gt;
The ring \(\mathscr{O}_p\) is the direct limit of the \(\mathscr{O}(U)\)
as \(U\) varies over the open neighborhoods of \(p\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that there is a surjection \(\mathscr{O}_p \to \mathbb{R}\)
that sends the germ of \(f\) at \(p\) to \(f(p)\in \mathbb{R}\).
The definition is independent of the choice of representative \(f\).
Since \(\mathbb{R}\) is a field, the kernel of the map
is a maximal ideal; let’s call it \(\mathfrak{m}_p\).
Observe that 
\(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2\) is a module over
\(\mathscr{O}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p \cong \mathbb{R}\), 
i.e. a real vector space;
we will call it the &lt;em&gt;algebraic cotangent space at \(p\).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-usual-cotangent-space&quot;&gt;The Usual Cotangent Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We retain our manifold \(X\) and point \(p\) from the previous section.
The &lt;em&gt;tangent space at \(p\),&lt;/em&gt; denoted \(T_pX\)
can be thought of as the space of “directions” in \(X\) at \(p\).
This is made precise by defining it to be the space of
directional &lt;em&gt;derivatives&lt;/em&gt; at \(p\).
I won’t attempt to make this more precise, except to note that
after we choose local coordinates \((x_1,\dotsc,x_n)\) near \(p = (p_1,\dotsc,p_n)\),
a basis for \(T_pX\) is given by&lt;/p&gt;

\[\frac{\partial}{\partial x_1}\bigg|_p,\dotsc, \frac{\partial}{\partial x_n}\bigg|_p.\]

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;cotangent space,&lt;/em&gt; which we are more interested in, is the
&lt;em&gt;dual&lt;/em&gt; of the tangent space and is denoted \(T_p^\ast X\).
Elements of the cotangent space are &lt;em&gt;linear functionals&lt;/em&gt; on tangent vectors.
Given coordinates \(x_1,\dotsc,x_n\),
the &lt;em&gt;dual basis&lt;/em&gt; of the cotangent space is given by&lt;/p&gt;

\[dx_1,\dotsc, dx_n,\]

&lt;p&gt;so we have \(dx_i\left( \frac{\partial}{\partial x_j}|_p\right)\) equal to \(1\)
when \(i = j\) and equal to \(0\) otherwise.
(There perhaps ought to be some notational inclusion of the point \(p\),
but we will suppress this.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-algebraic-cotangent-space-agrees-with-the-usual-one&quot;&gt;The Algebraic Cotangent Space Agrees With the Usual One&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If \(f\) is a smooth function on an open neighborhood of \(p\)
satisfying \(f(p) = 0\),
abusing notation, we shall write the corresponding element of
\(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2\)
as \(f + \mathfrak{m}_p^2\).
Given such an element,
I claim we can interpret \(f\) as a linear functional on tangent vectors at \(p\)
by sending a tangent vector \(v\) to the value of the derivative of \(f\) at \(p\) in the direction \(v\).
For instance, in local coordinates \((x_1,\dotsc,x_n)\),
the vector \(\frac{\partial}{\partial x_i}|_p\) is sent to \(\frac{\partial f}{\partial x_i}(p)\).
Extending linearly defines a linear functional on \(T_pX\),
which we shall denote \(df_p\).
The value of the directional derivative of a function depends only on its germ
essentially by definition,
and the product rule from calculus tells us that the assignment
\(f \mapsto df_p\) sends elements of \(\mathfrak{m}_p^2\) to the zero functional.
The linearity of the derivative implies that \(\mathbb{R}\)-linear combinations
of germs are sent to \(\mathbb{R}\)-linear combinations of functionals,
so the assignment&lt;/p&gt;

\[f + \mathfrak{m}_p^2 \mapsto df_p\]

&lt;p&gt;really defines a map \(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 \to T_p^\ast X\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We claim this map is an isomorphism, for which it suffices to define an inverse.
Choose local coordinates \(\vec x = (x_1,\dotsc,x_n)\) around \(\vec p = (p_1,\dotsc,p_n)\).
A general element \(\alpha\) of \(T_p^\ast X\)
may be written as the linear combination
\(\alpha = a_1\mathop{dx_1} + \dotsb + a_n\mathop{dx_n}.\)
Write \(\vec a = (a_1,\dotsc,a_n)\).
The function \(f_\alpha\) defined as&lt;/p&gt;

\[f_\alpha(\vec x) = \vec a\cdot(\vec x - \vec p)\]

&lt;p&gt;clearly has germ belonging to \(\mathfrak{m}_p\),
and tracing the double composition,
we see that we have \(a \mapsto f_\alpha + \mathfrak{m}_p^2 \mapsto d(f_\alpha)_p = \alpha\).
This map will be an isomorphism as soon as we can show that the germ of
\(f - f_{df_p}\) belongs to \(\mathfrak{m}_p^2\), i.e.
can be written as \(g_1h_1 + \dotsb g_kh_k\) for some
smooth functions \(g_i\) and \(h_i\) whose germs belong to \(\mathfrak{m}_p\).
This is the statement of Taylor’s theorem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even better, the map \(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 \to T_p^\ast X\)
is a &lt;em&gt;natural isomorphism,&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that given a smooth map
\(\varphi\colon X \to Y\) of smooth manifolds such that
\(\varphi(p) = q\), the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}
	\begin{CD}
		\mathfrak{m}_q/\mathfrak{m}_q^2 @&amp;gt;{\cong}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; T_q^\ast Y \\
		@VV{\varphi^\ast}V @VV{\varphi^\ast}V \\
		\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 @&amp;gt;{\cong}&amp;gt;&amp;gt; T_p^\ast X.
	\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;To verify this, we shall follow an element \(f + \mathfrak{m}_q^2\)
around the diagram&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{CD}
		f + \mathfrak{m}^2_q @&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; df_q \\
		@VVV @VVV \\
		f\varphi + \mathfrak{m}_p^2 @&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d(f\varphi)_p = \mathop{df_q}\mathop{d\varphi_p},
	\end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;and the fact that equality holds is the multi-variable chain rule!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having exploited our knowledge of undegraduate calculus to prove a satisfying
natural isomorphism,
I’ll leave you with one final reason this proof excites me.
If we had wanted to, we could have replaced “differentiable” with “continuous”
in our definition of the algebraic cotangent space,
and we would still end up with a real vector space associated to every stalk.
In some sense, I guessed that this says that the only reason one never speaks of a (co)tangent
space associated to a point in a general topological space is that
there’s no reason—like Taylor’s theorem—for the space to be finite-dimensional!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the truth is slightly more subtle:
every continuous function has a continuous “square root” in the sense
that we can always write \(f(x) = \operatorname{sgn}(f(x))\sqrt{f(x)}\sqrt{f(x)}\),
and the functions \(\sqrt{f}\) and \(\operatorname{sgn}(f)\sqrt(f)\) are continuous.
Therefore it is \(\mathfrak{m}_p\) that is infinite-dimensional,
while \(\mathfrak{m}_p/\mathfrak{m}_p^2 = 0\).
(Thanks to Curtis Heberle and Christopher Davis for pointing out my error!)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There is a “sheaf-theoretic” definition of something like a cotangent space at a point for a locally-ringed space. In the case of the sheaf of differentiable functions on a smooth manifold, the two definitions—sheaf-theoretic and the usual one in differential geometry—agree. What’s more, modulo the appropriate background technology in both subjects, the proof is beautiful and simple—I feel like shouting it from the rooftops at the moment, so this blog post will try and give a little exposition. I’ll try to move briskly without assuming total familiarity with either side of things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Orbifolds Day One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/05/Orbifolds-Day-One.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Orbifolds Day One" /><published>2020-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/05/Orbifolds-Day-One</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/05/Orbifolds-Day-One.html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/OrbifoldNotes1.pdf&quot;&gt;some notes&lt;/a&gt; introducing orbifolds from Haefliger’s perspective in &lt;em&gt;Metric Spaces of Non-positive Curvature&lt;/em&gt;.
There is some surprisingly heavy machinery that goes into it.
In this blog post I want to talk a little about it at a high level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;orbifold&lt;/em&gt; of dimension \(n\) is a Hausdorff space locally modeled on \(\mathbb{R}^n\) modulo
the action of a finite group.
This is a simple enough idea on its face:
a useful perspective on the fundamental group of a manifold 
is the passage between its action on the universal cover
and the calculus of loops in the base space.
For a group \(G\) that acts merely properly discontinuously and not freely,
the quotient space is no longer a manifold,
and yet we would like to accesss the “loops” perspective regardless.
This is the idea that orbifolds are trying to capture.
It is maybe surprising both how successful this project is,
and yet how much more complex the theory becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s remember back to when we learned Calculus.
First we learned how to manipulate real-valued functions of one variable,
and later multivariable functions \(f\colon \mathbb{R}^m \to \mathbb{R}^n\).
In particular, we defined a notion of differentiability for these maps.
To replicate this effort on differentiable manifolds,
one uses &lt;em&gt;charts.&lt;/em&gt; The idea is that the local structure of a manifold \(M\)
can be captured by a map \(\varphi\colon U \to M\), where \(U\) is an
open subset of \(\mathbb{R}^n\).
A map of manifolds \(f\colon M \to N\) is &lt;em&gt;defined&lt;/em&gt; to be differentiable
if its expression in any pair of charts is differentiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ridiculously maximalist approach to this idea is the following:
suppose \((U_i,\varphi_i)_{i\in I}\) is an &lt;em&gt;atlas&lt;/em&gt; for \(M\)
(in the usual sense), and that \((V_j,\psi_j)_{j\in J}\)
is an atlas for \(N\).
A function \(f\colon M \to N\)
defines a map \(f_{ij}\colon U_i \to V_j\)
whenever \(f\varphi_i(U_i) \subset \psi_j(V_j)\).
By refining the open cover of \(M\), we can assume this is always the case.
We can do the following strange thing:
the disjoint union \(U = \coprod_{i\in I}U_i\)
is a differentiable manifold, each of whose components is an open subset of \(\mathbb{R}^m\),
and the resulting map \(\varphi = \coprod_{i\in I}\varphi_i\) is differentiable
(in fact a local diffeomorphism).
The maps \(f_{ij}\) assemble into a map \(F\colon U \to V\) such that the following diagram commutes&lt;/p&gt;

\[\require{AMScd}\begin{CD} U @&amp;gt;F&amp;gt;&amp;gt; V \\ @VV\varphi V @VV\psi V \\ M @&amp;gt;f&amp;gt;&amp;gt; N. \end{CD}\]

&lt;p&gt;And we are justified in saying that \(f\) is differentiable when there exists
a map \(F\) constructed as above.
What we have done, essentially, is said that we don’t understand the quotient manifold,
but we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; understand open subsets of \(\mathbb{R}^m\), and have performed
a non-unique but useful construction to exploit that understanding.
This is the jumping-off point for orbifolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is just one more wrinkle: 
the definition of an atlas includes various differentiable maps
called &lt;em&gt;changes of charts.&lt;/em&gt; It would be convenient if there
were a way to stipulate that our map \(F\) must play nicely with these changes of charts
beyond just saying that there exists a map on the quotient space.
This is where Lie Groupoids come in: they turn out to be precisely the gadget we need
to manage the expression of \(f\) in charts while asserting that these expressions
play nicely with the changes of charts.
I’ll let you read the notes—and Haefliger too, hopefully.
Next time I’ll try to wrap my head around the fundamental group of an orbifold,
and hopefully thereafter the mapping class group of an orbifold.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I wrote some notes introducing orbifolds from Haefliger’s perspective in Metric Spaces of Non-positive Curvature. There is some surprisingly heavy machinery that goes into it. In this blog post I want to talk a little about it at a high level.</summary></entry></feed>